<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">

  <title><![CDATA[Category: Theory | Spekkionu's MTG Blog]]></title>
  <link href="http://www.spekkionu.com/category/theory/atom.xml" rel="self"/>
  <link href="http://www.spekkionu.com/"/>
  <updated>2015-01-25T20:30:55-08:00</updated>
  <id>http://www.spekkionu.com/</id>
  <author>
    <name><![CDATA[Jonathan Bernardi]]></name>
    
  </author>
  <generator uri="http://octopress.org/">Octopress</generator>

  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[Magic Workstation Guide]]></title>
    <link href="http://www.spekkionu.com/2006/06/magic-workstation-guide/"/>
    <updated>2006-06-22T16:31:41-07:00</updated>
    <id>http://www.spekkionu.com/2006/06/magic-workstation-guide</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>As I&rsquo;ve mentioned many times before I use <a href="http://www.magicworkstation.com/">Magic Workstation</a> for my deck building and testing.  Jason mentioned that a guide on how to use this program would make for a helpful article.  This article will assume you already have the program installed and set up with all the proper sets and images.  It will focus more on the actual use of the program.</p>

<!--more-->


<h2>Building Decks</h2>

<p>The first thing to do if you have not done so already is to click on View then Deck Edit Mode.  This will make working on a deck much easier.  You can also click on Columns Manager in the same View menu in order to edit what information is displayed about each card.  You can display whatever you want; Qty and Name are important enough to be required and Cost and Type are also very helpful.  I&rsquo;d advise to keep it simple and not display too much.  The less information is on the screen the easier it is to process in your mind.</p>

<p>Now we can go about building a deck.  There are a number of arrows in the column in the middle of the screen.  These arrows lets you manipulate the contents of the deck.  The blue arrow adds the selected card to the deck.  The green arrow adds it to the sideboard, and the red one removes the selected card from the deck or sideboard.  The grey arrows at the bottom move the selected card between the sideboard and maindeck.</p>

<p>Once the deck is finished save it like you would in any program.</p>

<p>There are also some things you can do to the library to make deck building easier.</p>

<p>You can right click the library column and select Card Filter (or find the same option in the View menu).  This will bring up a dialog box that will let you filter out certain sets. colors, rarities, or whatever.  Say you wanted to build a Standard legal deck.  Selecting Standard (T2) from the drop down box should select the proper sets if your program is up to date but you can select them manually if you like.  Once you hit okay only Standard legal cards will show up in the card library.  You can get rid of any filters by selecting Reset Filters.</p>

<p>One other setting you may want on is if you click on Show only Unique Cards from the View menu it will only display one of each card in the library.  This means you wont have a few dozen of each Basic Land on the list but also take away your option to choose which version of the card you are adding to the deck.</p>

<p>If you click on Deep Deck Analysis in the Tools menu it brings up a dialog box with a number of helpful features in it.  The first page, Probability Analysis, will let you calculate the odds of drawing a certain card or combination of cards.  The second page, Statistical Analysis, will let you determine the offs of having certain numbers of lands in your opening hand for mulligan purposes.  Rather than just calculating the probabilities like the first page this one runs through a set number of sample hands (which you set) and displays the results.  The George Baxter Analysis will tell you how many of each color mana sources your deck needs.  Note that this is not the same thing as how many lands to run.  This really just covers how many of each color source is recommended to not get color screwed as often.  A dual land would count as one of each color for this purpose.  You can also change the cost of any of the cards for the purposes of this analysis or how important they are.  Say you wanted <a class="mtg-card-link" rel="#mtg-card-popup" href="http://gatherer.wizards.com/Handlers/Image.ashx?size=small&type=card&name=Decree%20of%20Justice&options=" data-card="Decree of Justice">Decree of Justice</a> to count as one white mana rather than two since you will almost always cycle it rather than hard cast it.</p>

<p>Another pair of handy features are the Copy Deck to Clipboard and Paste Deck from Clipboard options in the Tools menu.  You can copy a decklist from say an article and use this feature to paste the decklist into MWS.  It may choke on a few cards but for the most part works pretty well assuming the deck isn&rsquo;t full of nicknames or spelling errors.  Say you wanted to copy a deck you saw online.  Rather than manually input each card and build the deck yourself you can have MWS do the work for you.  First copy the decklist to the clipboard (highlight it can copy it like any bit of text).  Then chose Paste Deck from Clipboard from the Tools menu.  This will bring up a dialog box with the deck in it.  Fix any spelling errors present in the list if necessary and make sure only one card is on each line.  Once you click the Work With It button it should import the decklist.  It generally isn&rsquo;t able to tell what the sideboard is so if the decklist had a sideboard it will usually put all the cards into the maindeck.  Just use the grey arrows to fix this.  You can also add any of the cards it had problems with.  If you want to save the deck make sure the deckbuilder is selected and go to Save As in the File menu rather than just hit the save button.</p>

<h2>Playing a Solo Game</h2>

<p>Now that our deck is built it is time to test it.  To begin a game click on Test Deck in Solo Mode in the Game menu.  The dialog box that pops up will be different depending on whether you have purchased the full version of the software.  With a full version of the software you will be able to choose a different deck for each player.  The trail version forces both players to use the same deck.  Once you have chosen the decks for each player you can start the game.</p>

<p>I&rsquo;ll now discuss the layout of the game screen.</p>

<p>First take a look at the menu at the top.  Most of the options are easy enough to figure out but note that the two sections in the view menu are separated by players (My Hand, My Graveyard vs. Opponent&rsquo;s Hand, Opponent&rsquo;s Graveyard&hellip;).  In these MY refers to the active player and Opponent to the non-active player rather than to Player A and Player B.</p>

<p>The icons in the center of the play area refer to the phases of a turn.  When you mouse over one an explanation pops up in the box on the upper-right.  That same box will display a card if you mouse over it.</p>

<p>Remember that unlike Magic Online, MWS does not know the rules or what any of the cards do so it is up you you to manipulate them the same way you would when playing with real cards.  This means it is up to you to remember to draw cards and to put two cards back on your library after casting <a class="mtg-card-link" rel="#mtg-card-popup" href="http://gatherer.wizards.com/Handlers/Image.ashx?size=small&type=card&name=Brainstorm&options=" data-card="Brainstorm">Brainstorm</a> or that <a class="mtg-card-link" rel="#mtg-card-popup" href="http://gatherer.wizards.com/Handlers/Image.ashx?size=small&type=card&name=Darksteel%20Ingot&options=" data-card="Darksteel Ingot">Darksteel Ingot</a> doesn&rsquo;t go to the graveyard when <a class="mtg-card-link" rel="#mtg-card-popup" href="http://gatherer.wizards.com/Handlers/Image.ashx?size=small&type=card&name=Shatter&options=" data-card="Shatter">Shattered</a>.</p>

<p>To change life totals you can either right click the life total and choose how to change it or double click it and enter a new life total.  Holding shift and clicking on a life total or a creature will signify there is damage being dealt to it.  You will still need to actually subtract two life or put the dead creature into the graveyard manually.  The numbers are just a way of visually showing the damage for something like splitting combat damage.</p>

<p>Right clicking the library will show you a number of options including being able to look at (and manipulate) the top X cards of your library.  Similar options are available for the graveyard, hand, and removed from game zone.</p>

<p>If a card is in play you can right click and drag the mouse pointer to another card or player.  This will draw a little arrow to signify something being targeted.  Once again this is optional but a nice visual representation of what is going on.</p>

<p>Clicking on one of the mana symbols by the life totals will increment counters to help you keep track of mana in your pool.  Right clicking will decrement the counter.  You can use these to keep track of anything else you want as well (such as storm count).</p>

<p>You can right click on a card in play and choose Set Note to put some text on a card.  This can be something to remind you about something on the card.  An example could be something like you can make a note on a card to signify that it is flipped.</p>

<p>One important thing to note, especially if you are just testing a deck, is that all of these fancy features are completely optional.  Manually clicking on each phase of the turn, and setting attacking creatures as attacking and blockers as blocking, and putting damage on the stack before resolving is completely unnecessary and very time consuming.  You are just getting a feel for how the deck plays and aren&rsquo;t even playing against a real person.  This is different if you are playing online or over a LAN or something but for testing purposes you really only need the program to keep track of life totals and what cards you draw and are in play.</p>

<h2>How to Test a Deck</h2>

<p>I&rsquo;m going to go through an actual testing session as an example.  The deck I&rsquo;ll be testing is a <a class="mtg-card-link" rel="#mtg-card-popup" href="http://gatherer.wizards.com/Handlers/Image.ashx?size=small&type=card&name=Pox&options=" data-card="Pox">Pox</a> deck I built a while ago.</p>

<p><div class="mtg-card-deck"><h3 class="mtg-card-deck-title">Pox</h3><div class="mtg-card-deck-content">
<div class="mtg-card-list"><h4>Lands (5)</h4><ul><li><a class="mtg-card-link" rel="#mtg-card-popup" href="http://gatherer.wizards.com/Handlers/Image.ashx?size=small&type=card&name=%3Cem%3E1%20Strip%20Mine&options=" data-card="&lt;em&gt;1 Strip Mine"><em>1 Strip Mine</a></li><li><a class="mtg-card-link" rel="#mtg-card-popup" href="http://gatherer.wizards.com/Handlers/Image.ashx?size=small&type=card&name=%3C/em%3E1%20Lake%20of%20the%20Dead&options=" data-card="&lt;/em&gt;1 Lake of the Dead"></em>1 Lake of the Dead</a></li><li><a class="mtg-card-link" rel="#mtg-card-popup" href="http://gatherer.wizards.com/Handlers/Image.ashx?size=small&type=card&name=%3Cem%3E11%20Swamp&options=" data-card="&lt;em&gt;11 Swamp"><em>11 Swamp</a></li><li><a class="mtg-card-link" rel="#mtg-card-popup" href="http://gatherer.wizards.com/Handlers/Image.ashx?size=small&type=card&name=%3C/em%3E4%20Wasteland&options=" data-card="&lt;/em&gt;4 Wasteland"></em>4 Wasteland</a></li><li><a class="mtg-card-link" rel="#mtg-card-popup" href="http://gatherer.wizards.com/Handlers/Image.ashx?size=small&type=card&name=%3Cem%3E4%20Peat%20Bog&options=" data-card="&lt;em&gt;4 Peat Bog"><em>4 Peat Bog</a></li></ul></div>
<div class="mtg-card-list"><h4>Creatures (1)</h4><ul><li><a class="mtg-card-link" rel="#mtg-card-popup" href="http://gatherer.wizards.com/Handlers/Image.ashx?size=small&type=card&name=%3C/em%3E2%20Nether%20Spirit&options=" data-card="&lt;/em&gt;2 Nether Spirit"></em>2 Nether Spirit</a></li></ul></div>
<div class="mtg-card-list"><h4>Spells (12)</h4><ul><li><a class="mtg-card-link" rel="#mtg-card-popup" href="http://gatherer.wizards.com/Handlers/Image.ashx?size=small&type=card&name=%3Cem%3E4%20Chimeric%20Idol&options=" data-card="&lt;em&gt;4 Chimeric Idol"><em>4 Chimeric Idol</a></li><li><a class="mtg-card-link" rel="#mtg-card-popup" href="http://gatherer.wizards.com/Handlers/Image.ashx?size=small&type=card&name=%3C/em%3E2%20Spinning%20Darkness&options=" data-card="&lt;/em&gt;2 Spinning Darkness"></em>2 Spinning Darkness</a></li><li><a class="mtg-card-link" rel="#mtg-card-popup" href="http://gatherer.wizards.com/Handlers/Image.ashx?size=small&type=card&name=%3Cem%3E4%20Pox&options=" data-card="&lt;em&gt;4 Pox"><em>4 Pox</a></li><li><a class="mtg-card-link" rel="#mtg-card-popup" href="http://gatherer.wizards.com/Handlers/Image.ashx?size=small&type=card&name=%3C/em%3E4%20Duress&options=" data-card="&lt;/em&gt;4 Duress"></em>4 Duress</a></li><li><a class="mtg-card-link" rel="#mtg-card-popup" href="http://gatherer.wizards.com/Handlers/Image.ashx?size=small&type=card&name=%3Cem%3E4%20Hymn%20to%20Tourach&options=" data-card="&lt;em&gt;4 Hymn to Tourach"><em>4 Hymn to Tourach</a></li><li><a class="mtg-card-link" rel="#mtg-card-popup" href="http://gatherer.wizards.com/Handlers/Image.ashx?size=small&type=card&name=%3C/em%3E4%20Diabolic%20Edict&options=" data-card="&lt;/em&gt;4 Diabolic Edict"></em>4 Diabolic Edict</a></li><li><a class="mtg-card-link" rel="#mtg-card-popup" href="http://gatherer.wizards.com/Handlers/Image.ashx?size=small&type=card&name=%3Cem%3E4%20Cabal%20Therapy&options=" data-card="&lt;em&gt;4 Cabal Therapy"><em>4 Cabal Therapy</a></li><li><a class="mtg-card-link" rel="#mtg-card-popup" href="http://gatherer.wizards.com/Handlers/Image.ashx?size=small&type=card&name=%3C/em%3E3%20Crucible%20of%20Worlds&options=" data-card="&lt;/em&gt;3 Crucible of Worlds"></em>3 Crucible of Worlds</a></li><li><a class="mtg-card-link" rel="#mtg-card-popup" href="http://gatherer.wizards.com/Handlers/Image.ashx?size=small&type=card&name=%3Cem%3E4%20Dark%20Ritual&options=" data-card="&lt;em&gt;4 Dark Ritual"><em>4 Dark Ritual</a></li><li><a class="mtg-card-link" rel="#mtg-card-popup" href="http://gatherer.wizards.com/Handlers/Image.ashx?size=small&type=card&name=%3C/em%3E2%20Charcoal%20Diamond&options=" data-card="&lt;/em&gt;2 Charcoal Diamond"></em>2 Charcoal Diamond</a></li><li><a class="mtg-card-link" rel="#mtg-card-popup" href="http://gatherer.wizards.com/Handlers/Image.ashx?size=small&type=card&name=%3Cem%3E1%20Demonic%20Tutor&options=" data-card="&lt;em&gt;1 Demonic Tutor"><em>1 Demonic Tutor</a></li><li><a class="mtg-card-link" rel="#mtg-card-popup" href="http://gatherer.wizards.com/Handlers/Image.ashx?size=small&type=card&name=%3C/em%3E1%20Necropotence&options=" data-card="&lt;/em&gt;1 Necropotence"></em>1 Necropotence</a></li></ul></div>
</div></div></p>

<p>The first thing I&rsquo;ll be doing is goldfishing the deck a few times.</p>

<p>I start a Solo game and draw my opening hand.  Its got lands and spells and is a keeper.  I&rsquo;m just goldfishing so it isn&rsquo;t important to pay attention to my opponent.  The turn will never be swapped.</p>

<p>After a turn 1 <a class="mtg-card-link" rel="#mtg-card-popup" href="http://gatherer.wizards.com/Handlers/Image.ashx?size=small&type=card&name=Duress&options=" data-card="Duress">Duress</a> I immediately untap and draw another card.  No need to go through turn phases so just a double click on the untap phase then the draw phase is all I&rsquo;ll ever need to hit.</p>

<p>I <a class="mtg-card-link" rel="#mtg-card-popup" href="http://gatherer.wizards.com/Handlers/Image.ashx?size=small&type=card&name=Dark%20Ritual&options=" data-card="Dark Ritual">Ritual</a> out a <a class="mtg-card-link" rel="#mtg-card-popup" href="http://gatherer.wizards.com/Handlers/Image.ashx?size=small&type=card&name=Chimeric%20Idol&options=" data-card="Chimeric Idol">Chimeric Idol</a> on turn three and drop another on turn four and <a class="mtg-card-link" rel="#mtg-card-popup" href="http://gatherer.wizards.com/Handlers/Image.ashx?size=small&type=card&name=Pox&options=" data-card="Pox">Pox</a> turn five.  This is enough for a first goldfish as it shows how the turns of the deck flow.  I&rsquo;d do a few more games like this until I&rsquo;m satisfied.</p>

<p>Now it is time to test the deck against an actual opponent (well opposing deck anyway).  I&rsquo;ll be playing both decks but need an opponent.</p>

<p>Note that in order to play a deck against a different deck in a solo game you would need to purchase the full version of MWS.  There is however a way to get around this.  Rather than play both decks on MWS you can use the program to play one deck and play the other deck with actual cards.  This would require to actually put one of the decks together (or at least proxy it) but would provide the same data as the full program would.</p>

<p>For the opposing deck I&rsquo;ll use the deck I always test a new deck against first, Snakes.</p>

<p><div class="mtg-card-deck"><h3 class="mtg-card-deck-title">Snakes</h3><div class="mtg-card-deck-content">
<div class="mtg-card-list"><h4>Lands (1)</h4><ul><li><a class="mtg-card-link" rel="#mtg-card-popup" href="http://gatherer.wizards.com/Handlers/Image.ashx?size=small&type=card&name=%3Cem%3E24%20Forest&options=" data-card="&lt;em&gt;24 Forest"><em>24 Forest</a></li></ul></div>
<div class="mtg-card-list"><h4>Creatures (7)</h4><ul><li><a class="mtg-card-link" rel="#mtg-card-popup" href="http://gatherer.wizards.com/Handlers/Image.ashx?size=small&type=card&name=%3C/em%3E4%20River%20Boa&options=" data-card="&lt;/em&gt;4 River Boa"></em>4 River Boa</a></li><li><a class="mtg-card-link" rel="#mtg-card-popup" href="http://gatherer.wizards.com/Handlers/Image.ashx?size=small&type=card&name=%3Cem%3E4%20Sosuke,%20Son%20of%20Seshiro&options=" data-card="&lt;em&gt;4 Sosuke, Son of Seshiro"><em>4 Sosuke, Son of Seshiro</a></li><li><a class="mtg-card-link" rel="#mtg-card-popup" href="http://gatherer.wizards.com/Handlers/Image.ashx?size=small&type=card&name=%3C/em%3E2%20Seshiro%20the%20Anointed&options=" data-card="&lt;/em&gt;2 Seshiro the Anointed"></em>2 Seshiro the Anointed</a></li><li><a class="mtg-card-link" rel="#mtg-card-popup" href="http://gatherer.wizards.com/Handlers/Image.ashx?size=small&type=card&name=%3Cem%3E4%20Orochi%20Ranger&options=" data-card="&lt;em&gt;4 Orochi Ranger"><em>4 Orochi Ranger</a></li><li><a class="mtg-card-link" rel="#mtg-card-popup" href="http://gatherer.wizards.com/Handlers/Image.ashx?size=small&type=card&name=%3C/em%3E2%20Tangle%20Asp&options=" data-card="&lt;/em&gt;2 Tangle Asp"></em>2 Tangle Asp</a></li><li><a class="mtg-card-link" rel="#mtg-card-popup" href="http://gatherer.wizards.com/Handlers/Image.ashx?size=small&type=card&name=%3Cem%3E4%20Sakura-Tribe%20Scout&options=" data-card="&lt;em&gt;4 Sakura-Tribe Scout"><em>4 Sakura-Tribe Scout</a></li><li><a class="mtg-card-link" rel="#mtg-card-popup" href="http://gatherer.wizards.com/Handlers/Image.ashx?size=small&type=card&name=%3C/em%3E4%20Sakura-Tribe%20Elder&options=" data-card="&lt;/em&gt;4 Sakura-Tribe Elder"></em>4 Sakura-Tribe Elder</a></li></ul></div>
<div class="mtg-card-list"><h4>Spells (6)</h4><ul><li><a class="mtg-card-link" rel="#mtg-card-popup" href="http://gatherer.wizards.com/Handlers/Image.ashx?size=small&type=card&name=%3Cem%3E4%20Sosuke&rsquo;s%20Summons&options=" data-card="&lt;em&gt;4 Sosuke&amp;rsquo;s Summons"><em>4 Sosuke&rsquo;s Summons</a></li><li><a class="mtg-card-link" rel="#mtg-card-popup" href="http://gatherer.wizards.com/Handlers/Image.ashx?size=small&type=card&name=%3C/em%3E4%20Aether%20Vial&options=" data-card="&lt;/em&gt;4 Aether Vial"></em>4 Aether Vial</a></li><li><span class="mtg-card-list-quantity">4</span> <a class="mtg-card-link" rel="#mtg-card-popup" href="http://gatherer.wizards.com/Handlers/Image.ashx?size=small&type=card&name=Overrun&options=" data-card="Overrun">Overrun</a></li></ul></div>
</div></div></p>

<p>After starting the game and drawing opening hands I use the Flip a Coin feature in the Action menu to see who plays first.  The <a class="mtg-card-link" rel="#mtg-card-popup" href="http://gatherer.wizards.com/Handlers/Image.ashx?size=small&type=card&name=Pox&options=" data-card="Pox">Pox</a> deck wins the die role and plays first.</p>

<p>A first turn <a class="mtg-card-link" rel="#mtg-card-popup" href="http://gatherer.wizards.com/Handlers/Image.ashx?size=small&type=card&name=Duress&options=" data-card="Duress">Duress</a> nabs an <a class="mtg-card-link" rel="#mtg-card-popup" href="http://gatherer.wizards.com/Handlers/Image.ashx?size=small&type=card&name=%C3%86ther%20Vial&options=" data-card="Æther Vial">Æther Vial</a>.  With <a class="mtg-card-link" rel="#mtg-card-popup" href="http://gatherer.wizards.com/Handlers/Image.ashx?size=small&type=card&name=Cabal%20Therapy&options=" data-card="Cabal Therapy">Cabal Therapy</a> in hand a note is made of what to name (probably the two copies of <a class="mtg-card-link" rel="#mtg-card-popup" href="http://gatherer.wizards.com/Handlers/Image.ashx?size=small&type=card&name=Overrun&options=" data-card="Overrun">Overrun</a>) and the turn is passed.</p>

<p>The Snake deck just plays a land and says go.  A <a class="mtg-card-link" rel="#mtg-card-popup" href="http://gatherer.wizards.com/Handlers/Image.ashx?size=small&type=card&name=Peat%20Bog&options=" data-card="Peat Bog">Peat Bog</a> is played and the Therapy for those two <a class="mtg-card-link" rel="#mtg-card-popup" href="http://gatherer.wizards.com/Handlers/Image.ashx?size=small&type=card&name=Overrun&options=" data-card="Overrun">Overruns</a>.  A turn two <a class="mtg-card-link" rel="#mtg-card-popup" href="http://gatherer.wizards.com/Handlers/Image.ashx?size=small&type=card&name=River%20Boa&options=" data-card="River Boa">River Boa</a> is sacked to <a class="mtg-card-link" rel="#mtg-card-popup" href="http://gatherer.wizards.com/Handlers/Image.ashx?size=small&type=card&name=Diabolic%20Edict&options=" data-card="Diabolic Edict">Diabolic Edict</a> and a second Therapy nabs a <a class="mtg-card-link" rel="#mtg-card-popup" href="http://gatherer.wizards.com/Handlers/Image.ashx?size=small&type=card&name=Sosuke&rsquo;s%20Summons&options=" data-card="Sosuke&amp;rsquo;s Summons">Sosuke&rsquo;s Summons</a> that was spotted with the last one.</p>

<p>The Snake deck gets it back after playing a <a class="mtg-card-link" rel="#mtg-card-popup" href="http://gatherer.wizards.com/Handlers/Image.ashx?size=small&type=card&name=Sakura-Tribe%20Scout&options=" data-card="Sakura-Tribe Scout">Sakura-Tribe Scout</a> but has no other plays.  The Pox deck drops <a class="mtg-card-link" rel="#mtg-card-popup" href="http://gatherer.wizards.com/Handlers/Image.ashx?size=small&type=card&name=Chimeric%20Idol&options=" data-card="Chimeric Idol">Chimeric Idol</a>.</p>

<p>The game plays out and snake tokens are traded for Idols until the Snake deck eventually overwhelms a mana-flooded Pox deck.</p>

<p>I normally play 3-4 games or so until I&rsquo;m happy with the results then start adjusting the deck if problems were exposed.  After some tweaking I usually test against another few decks of varying types and power levels before I&rsquo;m happy with a deck.  If the deck doesn&rsquo;t do very well in testing I usually scrap the idea completely rather than waste time on a lost cause.</p>

<p>Note how in this game cards like <a class="mtg-card-link" rel="#mtg-card-popup" href="http://gatherer.wizards.com/Handlers/Image.ashx?size=small&type=card&name=Cabal%20Therapy&options=" data-card="Cabal Therapy">Cabal Therapy</a> were played which require to make a guess at something that would normally be hidden (I got to remove the guessing part with <a class="mtg-card-link" rel="#mtg-card-popup" href="http://gatherer.wizards.com/Handlers/Image.ashx?size=small&type=card&name=Duress&options=" data-card="Duress">Duress</a> but that is irrelevant for this discussion).  This can be a bit difficult to do for some people as since you are controlling both players you know exactly what is in both hands.  You need to be able to objectively think what you would have named in that situation if you didn&rsquo;t know the correct answer.  This also applies to things like knowing which threats to counter and whether the opponent is holding mass removal so you can hold back a few threats.  This makes testing slightly less useful if you have problems with that type of thinking but I&rsquo;ve never found it all that difficult.</p>

<h2>Testing with the Evaluation Version</h2>

<p>Is I&rsquo;ve mention since the trial version of MWS only lets you pit a deck against itself rather that let you test various matchups you will need to work around this if you want the same data without paying the money for the full version.</p>

<p>The solution is actually quite simple.  You will only be using MWS to pilot one of the decks.  For the other deck you will use actual cards.</p>

<p>The first thing you need to do is build your decks.  Build one in MWS and the other with actual cards.  Start a solo game on MWS and shuffle up the real deck as well.  Draw your opening hand with the real deck and do the mulligan thing like normal with both decks.  Now instead of hitting the End Turn button on MWS each time you are finished just pick up the cards and play the real deck.  The only times this can be a more more awkward is when using things like local enchantments or switching control of permanents.  Even this isn&rsquo;t too odd as it isn&rsquo;t all that card to keep track of.  You can use notes or counters to keep track of things like that or create tokens to have a visual representation of something.</p>

<p>If you have no problems playing games like this you shouldn&rsquo;t need to purchase the full version of the software.  However one of the main things I use the program for is testing a deck before I purchase necessary cards for it to see if it is even worth building at all.  It kinda sucks to spend money on cards for a new deck only to later find out the deck is worthless.  You can proxy missing cards until then but that is quite a bit more effort and will eat up either your printer ink or your basic lands (or both) over large periods of time proxying many decks.</p>

<h2>Playing Online</h2>

<p>MWS also has the capability to play over TCP/IP with another opponent.  This feature is available in the free version as well.  I haven&rsquo;t used it however so I don&rsquo;t have any helpful tricks for it.  You do need to be pretty familiar with the software before trying it as you&rsquo;ll be playing an actual opponent and the program has nothing to prevent you from accidentally cheating.</p>

<h2>Apprentice</h2>

<p><a href="http://www.magic-league.com/download/apprentice.php">Apprentice</a> is a free alternative to MWS and has been around much longer and has a slightly larger support group (mostly due to being free and older).  They are both equivalent functionality-wise but MWS has a bit higher learning curve and Apprentice has none of the pretty visual effects MWS does.  This means no card images or mana symbols and the like.  If you can live without the pretty pictures and really don&rsquo;t want to pay for MWS it is certainly a good option.</p>

<p>Keep in mind that to solo a deck against another deck in Apprentice you need to open up two copies of the program and connect them to each other.  You would then switch windows to control each player.</p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[Ravnica Sleepers]]></title>
    <link href="http://www.spekkionu.com/2005/11/ravnica-sleepers/"/>
    <updated>2005-11-04T15:23:05-07:00</updated>
    <id>http://www.spekkionu.com/2005/11/ravnica-sleepers</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>A while ago I posted a set review of sorts for Ravnica. This is a bit of a follow up. Now that the set has been out a while I have more data to work with as far as experience playing with the cards goes. I also think I&rsquo;ve figured out what a few of the set&rsquo;s sleepers are. Once again I&rsquo;ll be ignoring insignificant or limited only cards and very obvious cards. You don&rsquo;t need me to tell you that <a class="mtg-card-link" rel="#mtg-card-popup" href="http://gatherer.wizards.com/Handlers/Image.ashx?size=small&type=card&name=Birds%20of%20Paradise&options=" data-card="Birds of Paradise">Birds of Paradise</a> is good, <a class="mtg-card-link" rel="#mtg-card-popup" href="http://gatherer.wizards.com/Handlers/Image.ashx?size=small&type=card&name=Watchwolf&options=" data-card="Watchwolf">Watchwolf</a> is very aggressivly costed, and <a class="mtg-card-link" rel="#mtg-card-popup" href="http://gatherer.wizards.com/Handlers/Image.ashx?size=small&type=card&name=Caregiver&options=" data-card="Caregiver">Caregiver</a> is bad. Also if I have nothing new to say since the last review I will leave it out here.</p>

<!--more-->


<p><a class="mtg-card-link" rel="#mtg-card-popup" href="http://gatherer.wizards.com/Handlers/Image.ashx?size=small&type=card&name=Bathe%20in%20Light&options=" data-card="Bathe in Light">Bathe in Light</a><br/>
This has turned out to be quite a nice little trick. While nothing amazing it is certainly playable in casual, especially multiplayer. It does have a bit of tournament value as well. One of its major bonus' is that it can make Auras fall off your creatures. Since cards like <a class="mtg-card-link" rel="#mtg-card-popup" href="http://gatherer.wizards.com/Handlers/Image.ashx?size=small&type=card&name=Threads%20of%20Disloyalty&options=" data-card="Threads of Disloyalty">Threads of Disloyalty</a> and <a class="mtg-card-link" rel="#mtg-card-popup" href="http://gatherer.wizards.com/Handlers/Image.ashx?size=small&type=card&name=Faith&rsquo;s%20Fetters&options=" data-card="Faith&amp;rsquo;s Fetters">Faith&rsquo;s Fetters</a> are seeing play this is significant. It also can be a nice <a class="mtg-card-link" rel="#mtg-card-popup" href="http://gatherer.wizards.com/Handlers/Image.ashx?size=small&type=card&name=Falter&options=" data-card="Falter">Falter</a> for breaking through stalemates.</p>

<p><a class="mtg-card-link" rel="#mtg-card-popup" href="http://gatherer.wizards.com/Handlers/Image.ashx?size=small&type=card&name=Bloodbond%20March&options=" data-card="Bloodbond March">Bloodbond March</a><br/>
This has been a bit disappointing in testing. While on paper I thought it looked like a solid engine for a casual deck after testing it I have decided it is in fact a piece of crap. I&rsquo;ve had better experiences with <a class="mtg-card-link" rel="#mtg-card-popup" href="http://gatherer.wizards.com/Handlers/Image.ashx?size=small&type=card&name=Disturbed%20Burial&options=" data-card="Disturbed Burial">Disturbed Burial</a>. It will see a lot of casual play anyway.</p>

<p><a class="mtg-card-link" rel="#mtg-card-popup" href="http://gatherer.wizards.com/Handlers/Image.ashx?size=small&type=card&name=Bloodletter%20Quill&options=" data-card="Bloodletter Quill">Bloodletter Quill</a><br/>
This is actually pretty decent but not as decent as <a class="mtg-card-link" rel="#mtg-card-popup" href="http://gatherer.wizards.com/Handlers/Image.ashx?size=small&type=card&name=Jushi%20Apprentice&options=" data-card="Jushi Apprentice">Jushi Apprentice</a>. Maybe it will see play in block or after Kamigawa block rotates out.</p>

<p><a class="mtg-card-link" rel="#mtg-card-popup" href="http://gatherer.wizards.com/Handlers/Image.ashx?size=small&type=card&name=Boros%20Fury-Shield&options=" data-card="Boros Fury-Shield">Boros Fury-Shield</a><br/>
This was seeing play for about a week. Then people realized this is just a bad <a class="mtg-card-link" rel="#mtg-card-popup" href="http://gatherer.wizards.com/Handlers/Image.ashx?size=small&type=card&name=Shining%20Shoal&options=" data-card="Shining Shoal">Shining Shoal</a>. Even casual players are generally better off with something like <a class="mtg-card-link" rel="#mtg-card-popup" href="http://gatherer.wizards.com/Handlers/Image.ashx?size=small&type=card&name=Kor%20Chant&options=" data-card="Kor Chant">Kor Chant</a> which can actually kill things.</p>

<p><a class="mtg-card-link" rel="#mtg-card-popup" href="http://gatherer.wizards.com/Handlers/Image.ashx?size=small&type=card&name=Boros%20Garrison&options=" data-card="Boros Garrison">Boros Garrison</a> / <a class="mtg-card-link" rel="#mtg-card-popup" href="http://gatherer.wizards.com/Handlers/Image.ashx?size=small&type=card&name=Dimir%20Aqueduct&options=" data-card="Dimir Aqueduct">Dimir Aqueduct</a> / <a class="mtg-card-link" rel="#mtg-card-popup" href="http://gatherer.wizards.com/Handlers/Image.ashx?size=small&type=card&name=Golgari%20Rot%20Farm&options=" data-card="Golgari Rot Farm">Golgari Rot Farm</a> / <a class="mtg-card-link" rel="#mtg-card-popup" href="http://gatherer.wizards.com/Handlers/Image.ashx?size=small&type=card&name=Selesnya%20Sanctuary&options=" data-card="Selesnya Sanctuary">Selesnya Sanctuary</a><br/>
I dismissed these as mediocre until I actually played with them. My opinion then became that they are decent. After playing even more with them I think they might actually be amazing. They are even seeing heavy tournament play as they take a lot of the sting out of cards like <a class="mtg-card-link" rel="#mtg-card-popup" href="http://gatherer.wizards.com/Handlers/Image.ashx?size=small&type=card&name=Suppression%20Field&options=" data-card="Suppression Field">Suppression Field</a> and <a class="mtg-card-link" rel="#mtg-card-popup" href="http://gatherer.wizards.com/Handlers/Image.ashx?size=small&type=card&name=Hokori&options=" data-card="Hokori">Hokori</a>. They will likely also keep <a class="mtg-card-link" rel="#mtg-card-popup" href="http://gatherer.wizards.com/Handlers/Image.ashx?size=small&type=card&name=Weathered%20Wayfarer&options=" data-card="Weathered Wayfarer">Weathered Wayfarer</a> from seeing much use.</p>

<p><a class="mtg-card-link" rel="#mtg-card-popup" href="http://gatherer.wizards.com/Handlers/Image.ashx?size=small&type=card&name=Boros%20Signet&options=" data-card="Boros Signet">Boros Signet</a> / <a class="mtg-card-link" rel="#mtg-card-popup" href="http://gatherer.wizards.com/Handlers/Image.ashx?size=small&type=card&name=Dimir%20Signet&options=" data-card="Dimir Signet">Dimir Signet</a> / <a class="mtg-card-link" rel="#mtg-card-popup" href="http://gatherer.wizards.com/Handlers/Image.ashx?size=small&type=card&name=Golgari%20Signet&options=" data-card="Golgari Signet">Golgari Signet</a> / <a class="mtg-card-link" rel="#mtg-card-popup" href="http://gatherer.wizards.com/Handlers/Image.ashx?size=small&type=card&name=Selesnya%20Signet&options=" data-card="Selesnya Signet">Selesnya Signet</a><br/>
These also wound up much better than I thought they would be. While not amazing by any means after testing them I&rsquo;ve decided they are slightly better than the <a class="mtg-card-link" rel="#mtg-card-popup" href="http://gatherer.wizards.com/Handlers/Image.ashx?size=small&type=card&name=Talisman%20of%20Dominance&options=" data-card="Talisman of Dominance">Talismans</a>.</p>

<p><a class="mtg-card-link" rel="#mtg-card-popup" href="http://gatherer.wizards.com/Handlers/Image.ashx?size=small&type=card&name=Boros%20Swiftblade&options=" data-card="Boros Swiftblade">Boros Swiftblade</a><br/>
Have you seen what happens when this guy picks up a <a class="mtg-card-link" rel="#mtg-card-popup" href="http://gatherer.wizards.com/Handlers/Image.ashx?size=small&type=card&name=Umezawa&rsquo;s%20Jitte&options=" data-card="Umezawa&amp;rsquo;s Jitte">Jitte</a>? He kills in two attack phases.</p>

<p><a class="mtg-card-link" rel="#mtg-card-popup" href="http://gatherer.wizards.com/Handlers/Image.ashx?size=small&type=card&name=Carven%20Caryatid&options=" data-card="Carven Caryatid">Carven Caryatid</a><br/>
Most definitely good but a good portion of the aggro decks rely on small flyers like <a class="mtg-card-link" rel="#mtg-card-popup" href="http://gatherer.wizards.com/Handlers/Image.ashx?size=small&type=card&name=Suntail%20Hawk&options=" data-card="Suntail Hawk">Suntail Hawk</a>, <a class="mtg-card-link" rel="#mtg-card-popup" href="http://gatherer.wizards.com/Handlers/Image.ashx?size=small&type=card&name=Leonin%20Skyhunter&options=" data-card="Leonin Skyhunter">Leonin Skyhunter</a>, and <a class="mtg-card-link" rel="#mtg-card-popup" href="http://gatherer.wizards.com/Handlers/Image.ashx?size=small&type=card&name=Hypnotic%20Specter&options=" data-card="Hypnotic Specter">Hypnotic Specter</a>. As long as they do this wont be living up to its full potential. Will likely have more success in Extended especially since <a class="mtg-card-link" rel="#mtg-card-popup" href="http://gatherer.wizards.com/Handlers/Image.ashx?size=small&type=card&name=Wall%20of%20Blossoms&options=" data-card="Wall of Blossoms">Wall of Blossoms</a> just left.</p>

<p><a class="mtg-card-link" rel="#mtg-card-popup" href="http://gatherer.wizards.com/Handlers/Image.ashx?size=small&type=card&name=Char&options=" data-card="Char">Char</a><br/>
This is seeing quite a bit of play in the Boros decks. The argument is generally between this and <a class="mtg-card-link" rel="#mtg-card-popup" href="http://gatherer.wizards.com/Handlers/Image.ashx?size=small&type=card&name=Shock&options=" data-card="Shock">Shock</a>. The smaller spell is better in the mirror and against <a class="mtg-card-link" rel="#mtg-card-popup" href="http://gatherer.wizards.com/Handlers/Image.ashx?size=small&type=card&name=Birds%20of%20Paradise&options=" data-card="Birds of Paradise">Birds of Paradise</a> and <a class="mtg-card-link" rel="#mtg-card-popup" href="http://gatherer.wizards.com/Handlers/Image.ashx?size=small&type=card&name=Hypnotic%20Specter&options=" data-card="Hypnotic Specter">Hypnotic Specter</a> but <a class="mtg-card-link" rel="#mtg-card-popup" href="http://gatherer.wizards.com/Handlers/Image.ashx?size=small&type=card&name=Char&options=" data-card="Char">Char</a> is better against control where it can go to the dome for extra reach. The fact that it kills <a class="mtg-card-link" rel="#mtg-card-popup" href="http://gatherer.wizards.com/Handlers/Image.ashx?size=small&type=card&name=Meloku%20the%20Clouded%20Mirror&options=" data-card="Meloku the Clouded Mirror">Meloku</a> is very significant.</p>

<p><a class="mtg-card-link" rel="#mtg-card-popup" href="http://gatherer.wizards.com/Handlers/Image.ashx?size=small&type=card&name=Circu,%20Dimir%20Lobotomist&options=" data-card="Circu, Dimir Lobotomist">Circu, Dimir Lobotomist</a><br/>
This has proven to be a casual play only card. While it still looks like fun it is very unreliable and too easy to kill to be competitive.</p>

<p><a class="mtg-card-link" rel="#mtg-card-popup" href="http://gatherer.wizards.com/Handlers/Image.ashx?size=small&type=card&name=Cloudstone%20Curio&options=" data-card="Cloudstone Curio">Cloudstone Curio</a><br/>
I had figured out this combo with this and 2 <a class="mtg-card-link" rel="#mtg-card-popup" href="http://gatherer.wizards.com/Handlers/Image.ashx?size=small&type=card&name=Crimson%20Kobolds&options=" data-card="Crimson Kobolds">Kobolds</a> to pump the storm count and finish with <a class="mtg-card-link" rel="#mtg-card-popup" href="http://gatherer.wizards.com/Handlers/Image.ashx?size=small&type=card&name=Brain%20Freeze&options=" data-card="Brain Freeze">Brain Freeze</a> or <a class="mtg-card-link" rel="#mtg-card-popup" href="http://gatherer.wizards.com/Handlers/Image.ashx?size=small&type=card&name=Tendrils%20of%20Agony&options=" data-card="Tendrils of Agony">Tendrils</a> and was happy that I had thought of something original. The very next day there was a list for that same deck on Brainburst. The day after that Starcity Games posted a different version. So much for me being original.</p>

<p><a class="mtg-card-link" rel="#mtg-card-popup" href="http://gatherer.wizards.com/Handlers/Image.ashx?size=small&type=card&name=Concerted%20Effort&options=" data-card="Concerted Effort">Concerted Effort</a><br/>
Casual players were hyping this up quite a bit. It is crap though so don&rsquo;t buy into it.</p>

<p><a class="mtg-card-link" rel="#mtg-card-popup" href="http://gatherer.wizards.com/Handlers/Image.ashx?size=small&type=card&name=Dark%20Confidant&options=" data-card="Dark Confidant">Dark Confidant</a><br/>
This guy popped up in quite a few decks at States. He is dangerous but extremely powerful. We&rsquo;ll see how well those black decks do from here on. I did see him in decks with expensive cards like <a class="mtg-card-link" rel="#mtg-card-popup" href="http://gatherer.wizards.com/Handlers/Image.ashx?size=small&type=card&name=Ink-Eyes,%20Servant%20of%20Oni&options=" data-card="Ink-Eyes, Servant of Oni">Ink-Eyes</a> and <a class="mtg-card-link" rel="#mtg-card-popup" href="http://gatherer.wizards.com/Handlers/Image.ashx?size=small&type=card&name=Kokusho,%20the%20Evening%20Star&options=" data-card="Kokusho, the Evening Star">Kokusho</a> which I would be too afraid to try. Then again I&rsquo;m afraid of <a class="mtg-card-link" rel="#mtg-card-popup" href="http://gatherer.wizards.com/Handlers/Image.ashx?size=small&type=card&name=Flesh%20Reaver&options=" data-card="Flesh Reaver">Flesh Reaver</a> and <a class="mtg-card-link" rel="#mtg-card-popup" href="http://gatherer.wizards.com/Handlers/Image.ashx?size=small&type=card&name=Phyrexian%20Negator&options=" data-card="Phyrexian Negator">Phyrexian Negator</a>. I think it would be good in a deck like Machine Head.</p>

<p><a class="mtg-card-link" rel="#mtg-card-popup" href="http://gatherer.wizards.com/Handlers/Image.ashx?size=small&type=card&name=Darkblast&options=" data-card="Darkblast">Darkblast</a><br/>
This probably wont make a large impact in Standard but expect to see a few copies in Extended, Vintage, and Legacy decks. It is basically the new <a class="mtg-card-link" rel="#mtg-card-popup" href="http://gatherer.wizards.com/Handlers/Image.ashx?size=small&type=card&name=Lava%20Dart&options=" data-card="Lava Dart">Lava Dart</a> in those formats.</p>

<p><a class="mtg-card-link" rel="#mtg-card-popup" href="http://gatherer.wizards.com/Handlers/Image.ashx?size=small&type=card&name=Dimir%20Cutpurse&options=" data-card="Dimir Cutpurse">Dimir Cutpurse</a><br/>
This combines with <a class="mtg-card-link" rel="#mtg-card-popup" href="http://gatherer.wizards.com/Handlers/Image.ashx?size=small&type=card&name=Hypnotic%20Specter&options=" data-card="Hypnotic Specter">Hypnotic Specter</a> as three drops a control deck never wants to see resolve. A number of B/U aggro decks made top 8 at States and most ran this guy.</p>

<p><a class="mtg-card-link" rel="#mtg-card-popup" href="http://gatherer.wizards.com/Handlers/Image.ashx?size=small&type=card&name=Dimir%20Doppelganger&options=" data-card="Dimir Doppelganger">Dimir Doppelganger</a><br/>
This is actually quite good. It is a great reanimator engine and also has potential to do a lot of other wacky things like <a class="mtg-card-link" rel="#mtg-card-popup" href="http://gatherer.wizards.com/Handlers/Image.ashx?size=small&type=card&name=Volrath&rsquo;s%20Shapeshifter&options=" data-card="Volrath&amp;rsquo;s Shapeshifter">Volrath&rsquo;s Shapeshifter</a> did. I imagine this will see a lot of casual play and was also in a few reanimator decks in States.</p>

<p><a class="mtg-card-link" rel="#mtg-card-popup" href="http://gatherer.wizards.com/Handlers/Image.ashx?size=small&type=card&name=Dimir%20House%20Guard&options=" data-card="Dimir House Guard">Dimir House Guard</a><br/>
This saw a bit of play at States. He just Transmutes into so many neat things like <a class="mtg-card-link" rel="#mtg-card-popup" href="http://gatherer.wizards.com/Handlers/Image.ashx?size=small&type=card&name=Cranial%20Extraction&options=" data-card="Cranial Extraction">Cranial Extraction</a> and <a class="mtg-card-link" rel="#mtg-card-popup" href="http://gatherer.wizards.com/Handlers/Image.ashx?size=small&type=card&name=Gifts%20Ungiven&options=" data-card="Gifts Ungiven">Gifts Ungiven</a>. Not too exciting as a creature in constructed though.</p>

<p><a class="mtg-card-link" rel="#mtg-card-popup" href="http://gatherer.wizards.com/Handlers/Image.ashx?size=small&type=card&name=Doubling%20Season&options=" data-card="Doubling Season">Doubling Season</a><br/>
I still like this card and haven&rsquo;t tried it yet. A lot of other causal players are though and it seems to be a nice casual staple. Don&rsquo;t expect it to see any tournament play though.</p>

<p><a class="mtg-card-link" rel="#mtg-card-popup" href="http://gatherer.wizards.com/Handlers/Image.ashx?size=small&type=card&name=Drift%20of%20Phantasms&options=" data-card="Drift of Phantasms">Drift of Phantasms</a><br/>
This is seeing a lot of play even in decks without many things to transmute into. It is great at blocking small flyers which is a nice thing to do right now. It also finds <a class="mtg-card-link" rel="#mtg-card-popup" href="http://gatherer.wizards.com/Handlers/Image.ashx?size=small&type=card&name=Threads%20of%20Disloyalty&options=" data-card="Threads of Disloyalty">Threads of Disloyalty</a>.</p>

<p><a class="mtg-card-link" rel="#mtg-card-popup" href="http://gatherer.wizards.com/Handlers/Image.ashx?size=small&type=card&name=Elves%20of%20Deep%20Shadow&options=" data-card="Elves of Deep Shadow">Elves of Deep Shadow</a><br/>
Combines with <a class="mtg-card-link" rel="#mtg-card-popup" href="http://gatherer.wizards.com/Handlers/Image.ashx?size=small&type=card&name=Birds%20of%20Paradise&options=" data-card="Birds of Paradise">Birds of Paradise</a> to maximize those chances of a turn 2 <a class="mtg-card-link" rel="#mtg-card-popup" href="http://gatherer.wizards.com/Handlers/Image.ashx?size=small&type=card&name=Hypnotic%20Specter&options=" data-card="Hypnotic Specter">Hypnotic Specter</a>.</p>

<p><a class="mtg-card-link" rel="#mtg-card-popup" href="http://gatherer.wizards.com/Handlers/Image.ashx?size=small&type=card&name=Eye%20of%20the%20Storm&options=" data-card="Eye of the Storm">Eye of the Storm</a><br/>
This was originally thought to be a casual only card. Then was going to be the engine for the next <a class="mtg-card-link" rel="#mtg-card-popup" href="http://gatherer.wizards.com/Handlers/Image.ashx?size=small&type=card&name=Heartbeat%20of%20Spring&options=" data-card="Heartbeat of Spring">Heartbeat of Spring</a> combo deck. Then people realized the Heartbeat decks kill without this and just left it out. Back to casual only.</p>

<p><a class="mtg-card-link" rel="#mtg-card-popup" href="http://gatherer.wizards.com/Handlers/Image.ashx?size=small&type=card&name=Faith&rsquo;s%20Fetters&options=" data-card="Faith&amp;rsquo;s Fetters">Faith&rsquo;s Fetters</a><br/>
This is a sleeper hit. It looks quite bad. Four mana for 4 life and a <a class="mtg-card-link" rel="#mtg-card-popup" href="http://gatherer.wizards.com/Handlers/Image.ashx?size=small&type=card&name=Pacifism&options=" data-card="Pacifism">Pacifism</a> doesn&rsquo;t look good but this is probably the best answer to <a class="mtg-card-link" rel="#mtg-card-popup" href="http://gatherer.wizards.com/Handlers/Image.ashx?size=small&type=card&name=Umezawa&rsquo;s%20Jitte&options=" data-card="Umezawa&amp;rsquo;s Jitte">Jitte</a> in the environment. It not only renders it useless but leaving it in play is quite significant. If you had just killed it with <a class="mtg-card-link" rel="#mtg-card-popup" href="http://gatherer.wizards.com/Handlers/Image.ashx?size=small&type=card&name=Terashi&rsquo;s%20Grasp&options=" data-card="Terashi&amp;rsquo;s Grasp">Terashi&rsquo;s Grasp</a> they would likely just drop a new one and continue beating. With the old one still there the legend rule would prevent them from easily replacing it. It essentially nullifies two <a class="mtg-card-link" rel="#mtg-card-popup" href="http://gatherer.wizards.com/Handlers/Image.ashx?size=small&type=card&name=Umezawa&rsquo;s%20Jitte&options=" data-card="Umezawa&amp;rsquo;s Jitte">Jittes</a> with one Aura. Gaining 4 life against WW doesn&rsquo;t hurt either.</p>

<p><a class="mtg-card-link" rel="#mtg-card-popup" href="http://gatherer.wizards.com/Handlers/Image.ashx?size=small&type=card&name=Firemane%20Angel&options=" data-card="Firemane Angel">Firemane Angel</a><br/>
I didn&rsquo;t think this was very good on paper. Six mana for a 4/3 Flying First Striker doesn&rsquo;t seem very exciting. The reanimation ability is so expensive that it will only be relevant once every three games or so. However It is still probably one of the best finishers the R/W control deck has right now. I would have liked an extra toughness to bring it out of <a class="mtg-card-link" rel="#mtg-card-popup" href="http://gatherer.wizards.com/Handlers/Image.ashx?size=small&type=card&name=Lightning%20Helix&options=" data-card="Lightning Helix">Lightning Helix</a> range though.</p>

<p><a class="mtg-card-link" rel="#mtg-card-popup" href="http://gatherer.wizards.com/Handlers/Image.ashx?size=small&type=card&name=Glare%20of%20Subdual&options=" data-card="Glare of Subdual">Glare of Subdual</a><br/>
There is a Japanese deck based around this card. If the Japanese are using it that is a good sign that it doesn&rsquo;t suck. They tend to be ahead of the game at deckbuilding. Will never even be considered in any format <a class="mtg-card-link" rel="#mtg-card-popup" href="http://gatherer.wizards.com/Handlers/Image.ashx?size=small&type=card&name=Opposition&options=" data-card="Opposition">Opposition</a> is legal in though.</p>

<p><a class="mtg-card-link" rel="#mtg-card-popup" href="http://gatherer.wizards.com/Handlers/Image.ashx?size=small&type=card&name=Gleancrawler&options=" data-card="Gleancrawler">Gleancrawler</a><br/>
This can be amazing or just solid. This will see huge amounts of casual play and possibly some tournament play. It has popped up in a States list or two.</p>

<p><a class="mtg-card-link" rel="#mtg-card-popup" href="http://gatherer.wizards.com/Handlers/Image.ashx?size=small&type=card&name=Glimpse%20the%20Unthinkable&options=" data-card="Glimpse the Unthinkable">Glimpse the Unthinkable</a><br/>
This is finally starting to drop in price but is still not an affordable card. It is seeing the most play now as a reanimator enabler since the mill deck is balls in constructed. I did see a few reanimator decks in the States results so this is the closest the deck has been to viable in Standard in a long time.</p>

<p><a class="mtg-card-link" rel="#mtg-card-popup" href="http://gatherer.wizards.com/Handlers/Image.ashx?size=small&type=card&name=Golgari%20Grave-Troll&options=" data-card="Golgari Grave-Troll">Golgari Grave-Troll</a>
This hasn&rsquo;t caught on yet. I&rsquo;m almost positive it will eventually even if just in causal play. Dredge.dec made some appearances at States but I didn&rsquo;t see too many running this guy. I think that he&rsquo;ll start to pop up a bit more eventually. This will likely be a sleeper hit.</p>

<p><a class="mtg-card-link" rel="#mtg-card-popup" href="http://gatherer.wizards.com/Handlers/Image.ashx?size=small&type=card&name=Grave-Shell%20Scarab&options=" data-card="Grave-Shell Scarab">Grave-Shell Scarab</a><br/>
This is about as good as it looks. A great engine for a slow beatdown deck like the Rock.</p>

<p><a class="mtg-card-link" rel="#mtg-card-popup" href="http://gatherer.wizards.com/Handlers/Image.ashx?size=small&type=card&name=Helldozer&options=" data-card="Helldozer">Helldozer</a><br/>
This can be a wrecking ball in casual. The fact that even if you aren&rsquo;t blowing up lands he is still aggressively costed makes him that much better. These can be great equalizers for all those multicolored lands that are popping up.</p>

<p><a class="mtg-card-link" rel="#mtg-card-popup" href="http://gatherer.wizards.com/Handlers/Image.ashx?size=small&type=card&name=Hunted%20Dragon&options=" data-card="Hunted Dragon">Hunted Dragon</a><br/>
This is the only Hunted creature that has proved worth it. It is even quite solid.</p>

<p><a class="mtg-card-link" rel="#mtg-card-popup" href="http://gatherer.wizards.com/Handlers/Image.ashx?size=small&type=card&name=Hunted%20Lammasu&options=" data-card="Hunted Lammasu">Hunted Lammasu</a><br/>
This was in a very large numbers of decks when people first started testing for States. Then after playtesting everyone started removing them and ranting about how horrible they were. Turns out a 4/4 isn&rsquo;t something you want your opponent to have.</p>

<p><a class="mtg-card-link" rel="#mtg-card-popup" href="http://gatherer.wizards.com/Handlers/Image.ashx?size=small&type=card&name=Hunted%20Horror&options=" data-card="Hunted Horror">Hunted Horror</a><br/>
This is seeing play in causal with <a class="mtg-card-link" rel="#mtg-card-popup" href="http://gatherer.wizards.com/Handlers/Image.ashx?size=small&type=card&name=Brand&options=" data-card="Brand">Brand</a>. While that can be amazing you tend to not have both by turn 2 with any kind of regularity.</p>

<p><a class="mtg-card-link" rel="#mtg-card-popup" href="http://gatherer.wizards.com/Handlers/Image.ashx?size=small&type=card&name=Last%20Gasp&options=" data-card="Last Gasp">Last Gasp</a><br/>
This is the best mono-black removal spell in at least 2-3 years. You have to go back to <a class="mtg-card-link" rel="#mtg-card-popup" href="http://gatherer.wizards.com/Handlers/Image.ashx?size=small&type=card&name=Smother&options=" data-card="Smother">Smother</a> and possibly even <a class="mtg-card-link" rel="#mtg-card-popup" href="http://gatherer.wizards.com/Handlers/Image.ashx?size=small&type=card&name=Diabolic%20Edict&options=" data-card="Diabolic Edict">Diabolic Edict</a> to find a better one. It doesn&rsquo;t kill <a class="mtg-card-link" rel="#mtg-card-popup" href="http://gatherer.wizards.com/Handlers/Image.ashx?size=small&type=card&name=Meloku%20the%20Clouded%20Mirror&options=" data-card="Meloku the Clouded Mirror">Meloku</a> though so it isn&rsquo;t perfect.</p>

<p><a class="mtg-card-link" rel="#mtg-card-popup" href="http://gatherer.wizards.com/Handlers/Image.ashx?size=small&type=card&name=Life%20from%20the%20Loam&options=" data-card="Life from the Loam">Life from the Loam</a><br/>
I really like this card. It just does so much. It not only is a nice engine on its own but also combines nicely with cycling lands and the cycle of threshold lands from Odyssey. Still doesn&rsquo;t make <a class="mtg-card-link" rel="#mtg-card-popup" href="http://gatherer.wizards.com/Handlers/Image.ashx?size=small&type=card&name=Nomad%20Stadium&options=" data-card="Nomad Stadium">Nomad Stadium</a> playable though. Unfortunately it costs way to much for me to get some. This will be the big sleeper hit of the set. Expect it to be selling for $8-10 in the near future.</p>

<p><a class="mtg-card-link" rel="#mtg-card-popup" href="http://gatherer.wizards.com/Handlers/Image.ashx?size=small&type=card&name=Lightning%20Helix&options=" data-card="Lightning Helix">Lightning Helix</a><br/>
This is the main removal spell of the environment. It has been a while since those 3-toughness creatures were in this much trouble.</p>

<p><a class="mtg-card-link" rel="#mtg-card-popup" href="http://gatherer.wizards.com/Handlers/Image.ashx?size=small&type=card&name=Overgrown%20Tomb&options=" data-card="Overgrown Tomb">Overgrown Tomb</a> / <a class="mtg-card-link" rel="#mtg-card-popup" href="http://gatherer.wizards.com/Handlers/Image.ashx?size=small&type=card&name=Sacred%20Foundry&options=" data-card="Sacred Foundry">Sacred Foundry</a> / <a class="mtg-card-link" rel="#mtg-card-popup" href="http://gatherer.wizards.com/Handlers/Image.ashx?size=small&type=card&name=Temple%20Garden&options=" data-card="Temple Garden">Temple Garden</a> / <a class="mtg-card-link" rel="#mtg-card-popup" href="http://gatherer.wizards.com/Handlers/Image.ashx?size=small&type=card&name=Watery%20Grave&options=" data-card="Watery Grave">Watery Grave</a><br/>
Just like everyone knew they would these are the most important cards of the set in Standard and Extended. They will likely continue to be as long as they are legal. I would like to see them drop to $15 like a normal chase rare though.</p>

<p><a class="mtg-card-link" rel="#mtg-card-popup" href="http://gatherer.wizards.com/Handlers/Image.ashx?size=small&type=card&name=Plague%20Boiler&options=" data-card="Plague Boiler">Plague Boiler</a><br/>
People are still finding out if this is good or not. My testing has shown it to be kinda meh but I haven&rsquo;t tried it too much.</p>

<p><a class="mtg-card-link" rel="#mtg-card-popup" href="http://gatherer.wizards.com/Handlers/Image.ashx?size=small&type=card&name=Putrefy&options=" data-card="Putrefy">Putrefy</a><br/>
This is still my favorite card in the set. It is seeing play in every deck that can conceivably cast in and some care splashing for it. One of the best removal spells ever printed and still my vote for best card in the set.</p>

<p><a class="mtg-card-link" rel="#mtg-card-popup" href="http://gatherer.wizards.com/Handlers/Image.ashx?size=small&type=card&name=Razia,%20Boros%20Archangel&options=" data-card="Razia, Boros Archangel">Razia, Boros Archangel</a><br/>
This is extremely expensive, multicolored, and has the creature type, Angel. This all but guarantees it to see large amounts of casual play. This is also popping up in reanimator decks though.</p>

<p><a class="mtg-card-link" rel="#mtg-card-popup" href="http://gatherer.wizards.com/Handlers/Image.ashx?size=small&type=card&name=Remand&options=" data-card="Remand">Remand</a><br/>
Not <a class="mtg-card-link" rel="#mtg-card-popup" href="http://gatherer.wizards.com/Handlers/Image.ashx?size=small&type=card&name=Memory%20Lapse&options=" data-card="Memory Lapse">Memory Lapse</a> but still a great tempo card. It buys the time you need for the slow control decks to take over.</p>

<p><a class="mtg-card-link" rel="#mtg-card-popup" href="http://gatherer.wizards.com/Handlers/Image.ashx?size=small&type=card&name=Savra,%20Queen%20of%20the%20Golgari&options=" data-card="Savra, Queen of the Golgari">Savra, Queen of the Golgari</a><br/>
I haven&rsquo;t seen it in action yet but it is seeing a lot of casual play. Casual players love sacrificing their creatures so it was kind of obvious.</p>

<p><a class="mtg-card-link" rel="#mtg-card-popup" href="http://gatherer.wizards.com/Handlers/Image.ashx?size=small&type=card&name=Searing%20Meditation&options=" data-card="Searing Meditation">Searing Meditation</a><br/>
This is much better than it looks. You can&rsquo;t discount cards like this since <a class="mtg-card-link" rel="#mtg-card-popup" href="http://gatherer.wizards.com/Handlers/Image.ashx?size=small&type=card&name=Lightning%20Rift&options=" data-card="Lightning Rift">Lightning Rift</a> proved so amazing. This isn&rsquo;t as good since its deck doesn&rsquo;t feed itself but I&rsquo;ve been working on this one and it has been performing quite well.</p>

<p><a class="mtg-card-link" rel="#mtg-card-popup" href="http://gatherer.wizards.com/Handlers/Image.ashx?size=small&type=card&name=Shadow%20of%20Doubt&options=" data-card="Shadow of Doubt">Shadow of Doubt</a><br/>
I still love this card. It saw a bit of play but most people were eventually removing them for <a class="mtg-card-link" rel="#mtg-card-popup" href="http://gatherer.wizards.com/Handlers/Image.ashx?size=small&type=card&name=Remand&options=" data-card="Remand">Remand</a> which actually plays quite similarly but isn&rsquo;t as narrow. It now really only sees play in sideboards as <a class="mtg-card-link" rel="#mtg-card-popup" href="http://gatherer.wizards.com/Handlers/Image.ashx?size=small&type=card&name=Remand&options=" data-card="Remand">Remand</a> #5-8.</p>

<p><a class="mtg-card-link" rel="#mtg-card-popup" href="http://gatherer.wizards.com/Handlers/Image.ashx?size=small&type=card&name=Sisters%20of%20Stone%20Death&options=" data-card="Sisters of Stone Death">Sisters of Stone Death</a><br/>
Another reanimator target for a casual deck. This is seeing quite a bit of casual play. I doubt it will see much use even in reanimator when it comes to tournament play though.</p>

<p><a class="mtg-card-link" rel="#mtg-card-popup" href="http://gatherer.wizards.com/Handlers/Image.ashx?size=small&type=card&name=Stinkweed%20Imp&options=" data-card="Stinkweed Imp">Stinkweed Imp</a><br/>
Don&rsquo;t be supprised if this sees tournament play. The dredge mechanic is very powerful if a bit slow and this is one of the better enablers for it. It popped up in a decklist or two at States.</p>

<p><a class="mtg-card-link" rel="#mtg-card-popup" href="http://gatherer.wizards.com/Handlers/Image.ashx?size=small&type=card&name=Sunforger&options=" data-card="Sunforger">Sunforger</a><br/>
This is seeing a bit of tournament play. I think the Fungus Fire decks that are using it are piles of crap but they supposedly doing quite well on Magic Online and did get a few States top 8s. The card is quite cool though.</p>

<p><a class="mtg-card-link" rel="#mtg-card-popup" href="http://gatherer.wizards.com/Handlers/Image.ashx?size=small&type=card&name=Suppression%20Field&options=" data-card="Suppression Field">Suppression Field</a><br/>
This was hyped to be amazing and people were removing Jitte from their WW deck to play this. Then it was shown to be annoying but not impossible to play around. The problem is that is doesn&rsquo;t make <a class="mtg-card-link" rel="#mtg-card-popup" href="http://gatherer.wizards.com/Handlers/Image.ashx?size=small&type=card&name=Meloku%20the%20Clouded%20Mirror&options=" data-card="Meloku the Clouded Mirror">Meloku</a> and <a class="mtg-card-link" rel="#mtg-card-popup" href="http://gatherer.wizards.com/Handlers/Image.ashx?size=small&type=card&name=Umezawa&rsquo;s%20Jitte&options=" data-card="Umezawa&amp;rsquo;s Jitte">Jitte</a> suck. It just makes them balanced. They should have had higher activation costs to begin with so this just makes them fair. You know a card is broken when you can triple the mana you need to spend on it and it is still amazing.</p>

<p><a class="mtg-card-link" rel="#mtg-card-popup" href="http://gatherer.wizards.com/Handlers/Image.ashx?size=small&type=card&name=Szadek,%20Lord%20of%20Secrets&options=" data-card="Szadek, Lord of Secrets">Szadek, Lord of Secrets</a><br/>
Casual players haven&rsquo;t really used him much yet but I expect that to change over time. He is just a perfect example of a card a casual player would love.</p>

<p><a class="mtg-card-link" rel="#mtg-card-popup" href="http://gatherer.wizards.com/Handlers/Image.ashx?size=small&type=card&name=Ursapine&options=" data-card="Ursapine">Ursapine</a><br/>
This is seeing a bit of casual play. I think it is decent but there are better things you can do with 5 mana.</p>

<p><a class="mtg-card-link" rel="#mtg-card-popup" href="http://gatherer.wizards.com/Handlers/Image.ashx?size=small&type=card&name=Vinelasher%20Kudzu&options=" data-card="Vinelasher Kudzu">Vinelasher Kudzu</a><br/>
This card is AMAZING! The more I test him the better he looks. I&rsquo;m getting to the point where I think he might be better than <a class="mtg-card-link" rel="#mtg-card-popup" href="http://gatherer.wizards.com/Handlers/Image.ashx?size=small&type=card&name=Quirion%20Dryad&options=" data-card="Quirion Dryad">Quirion Dryad</a>. It is fun to drop him on turn 2 and attack with a 5/5 on turn 3. Expect this to go up in price.</p>

<p><a class="mtg-card-link" rel="#mtg-card-popup" href="http://gatherer.wizards.com/Handlers/Image.ashx?size=small&type=card&name=Vitu-Ghazi,%20the%20City-Tree&options=" data-card="Vitu-Ghazi, the City-Tree">Vitu-Ghazi, the City-Tree</a><br/>
This is the win condition in the terrible looking Fungus Fire decks. Other than that I haven&rsquo;t seen much of it. It is pretty expensive to use.</p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[Card Advantage in Multiplayer]]></title>
    <link href="http://www.spekkionu.com/2005/05/card-advantage-in-multiplayer/"/>
    <updated>2005-05-18T14:42:46-07:00</updated>
    <id>http://www.spekkionu.com/2005/05/card-advantage-in-multiplayer</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>Card advantage can be a little different in multiplayer than in a duel.  Look at the most common way of determining card advantage in a duel, counting cards.  If player A plays a <a class="mtg-card-link" rel="#mtg-card-popup" href="http://gatherer.wizards.com/Handlers/Image.ashx?size=small&type=card&name=Terror&options=" data-card="Terror">Terror</a> on one of player B&rsquo;s two <a class="mtg-card-link" rel="#mtg-card-popup" href="http://gatherer.wizards.com/Handlers/Image.ashx?size=small&type=card&name=Serra%20Angel&options=" data-card="Serra Angel">Serra Angels</a> he traded his one card for his opponent&rsquo;s one card and did not create card advantage or disadvantage (this is called maintaining card parity).  If Player A had instead played <a class="mtg-card-link" rel="#mtg-card-popup" href="http://gatherer.wizards.com/Handlers/Image.ashx?size=small&type=card&name=Wrath%20of%20God&options=" data-card="Wrath of God">Wrath of God</a> and killed both <a class="mtg-card-link" rel="#mtg-card-popup" href="http://gatherer.wizards.com/Handlers/Image.ashx?size=small&type=card&name=Serra%20Angel&options=" data-card="Serra Angel">Serra Angels</a> he traded one card for his opponent&rsquo;s two cards.  This is a card advantage of +1.  Similarly if player B then plays <a class="mtg-card-link" rel="#mtg-card-popup" href="http://gatherer.wizards.com/Handlers/Image.ashx?size=small&type=card&name=Concentrate&options=" data-card="Concentrate">Concentrate</a> he trades his one card for three new cards gaining a card advantage of +2.  What we are doing is comparing the amount of cards lost/gained by each player.</p>

<p>How does this counting method work in lets say a 3 player game?  In the first example where player B&rsquo;s <a class="mtg-card-link" rel="#mtg-card-popup" href="http://gatherer.wizards.com/Handlers/Image.ashx?size=small&type=card&name=Serra%20Angel&options=" data-card="Serra Angel">Serra Angel</a> is killed by player A&rsquo;s <a class="mtg-card-link" rel="#mtg-card-popup" href="http://gatherer.wizards.com/Handlers/Image.ashx?size=small&type=card&name=Terror&options=" data-card="Terror">Terror</a>.  Player A still maintains card parity with player B but what does it look like from the perspective of player C?  Player A used one card to deal with one card of player B&rsquo;s.  This means from player C&rsquo;s point of view two of his opponent&rsquo;s cards were dealt with without using any of his own.  This is easily an example of card advantage.  He got a +1 card advantage relative with player A and +1 relative to player B.  If you go back to player A&rsquo;s point of view he ended up with card parity with player B and -1 card advantage with player B (or +1 card disadvantage).</p>

<p>So a one for one trade results in an overall card disadvantage but what about the second example where player A Wraths away player B&rsquo;s two Angels?  Player A&rsquo;s card advantage relative to player B is still +1 but what about to player C?  It would be -1 because player A used one card and did not deal with any of player C&rsquo;s cards.  Could you consider that player A ended up with card parity (since -1 + 1 = 0)?  He still used one card to deal with two so that can&rsquo;t be the answer but clearly this trade still benefits player C who just saw 3 cards go away without expending any of his own (+1 relative to player A and +2 relative to player B).  I don&rsquo;t think there is necessarily a clear cut easy way to count card advantage in multiplayer as there is in a duel.  Since every interaction happens differently from each player&rsquo;s point of view you can either look at it relative to each player or as a whole from a neutral position.  Which is the correct way?  I don&rsquo;t think either is either correct or incorrect which makes it not so easy to determine.  At the very least it is something interesting to think about that I haven&rsquo;t seen being discussed elsewhere.</p>

<p>So what does any of this matter and how can you take advantage of it?  Well one thing that should be very clear is that the best place to be in in player C&rsquo;s seat.  If you can get your opponent&rsquo;s to deal with each other&rsquo;s threats it can mean nothing but massive card advantage for you.  So what types of cards will encourage your opponents to deal with each other&rsquo;s threats?  Generally since you can&rsquo;t control what your opponents are playing you will have to provide them with the means to do it.  This generally means some type of symmetrical card.  I believe I have recently found a good one.</p>

<!--more-->


<p>I want to start by showing you this brief part of a conversation I had with Dustin.</p>

<blockquote><p><strong>Me:</strong> I made a <a class="mtg-card-link" rel="#mtg-card-popup" href="http://gatherer.wizards.com/Handlers/Image.ashx?size=small&type=card&name=Death%20Match&options=" data-card="Death Match">Death Match</a> deck.<br/>
<strong>Dustin:</strong> You are bad at Magic.</p></blockquote>

<p>Those were his exact words when I told him I built a deck around <a class="mtg-card-link" rel="#mtg-card-popup" href="http://gatherer.wizards.com/Handlers/Image.ashx?size=small&type=card&name=Death%20Match&options=" data-card="Death Match">Death Match</a>.  I think by now I&rsquo;ve proved to Dustin and everyone else that <a class="mtg-card-link" rel="#mtg-card-popup" href="http://gatherer.wizards.com/Handlers/Image.ashx?size=small&type=card&name=Death%20Match&options=" data-card="Death Match">Death Match</a> is indeed a good card in multiplayer but let&rsquo;s look at why.</p>

<p>In my deck especially playing against creature heavy decks <a class="mtg-card-link" rel="#mtg-card-popup" href="http://gatherer.wizards.com/Handlers/Image.ashx?size=small&type=card&name=Death%20Match&options=" data-card="Death Match">Death Match</a> is a card advantage machine.  Like any good player knows a good symmetrical card is never actually symmetrical.  The biggest example will always be <a class="mtg-card-link" rel="#mtg-card-popup" href="http://gatherer.wizards.com/Handlers/Image.ashx?size=small&type=card&name=Balance&options=" data-card="Balance">Balance</a>.  This card just oozes symmetry flavor-wise but in actual use is often one of the most one-sided cards in existence.  You will just not play it unless it will benefit you.  Now breaking the symmetry on <a class="mtg-card-link" rel="#mtg-card-popup" href="http://gatherer.wizards.com/Handlers/Image.ashx?size=small&type=card&name=Death%20Match&options=" data-card="Death Match">Death Match</a> is not as easy as <a class="mtg-card-link" rel="#mtg-card-popup" href="http://gatherer.wizards.com/Handlers/Image.ashx?size=small&type=card&name=Balance&options=" data-card="Balance">Balance</a> but still not too hard.  First you want to be able to use it.  This means running a lot of creatures.  But you don&rsquo;t want your opponent to be able to use it better than you (which if they are playing something like Elves would be easy for them to do).  This means three things.  First you want to run creatures that you don&rsquo;t care if someone tries to kill.  I went with creatures like <a class="mtg-card-link" rel="#mtg-card-popup" href="http://gatherer.wizards.com/Handlers/Image.ashx?size=small&type=card&name=Sakura-Tribe%20Elder&options=" data-card="Sakura-Tribe Elder">Sakura-Tribe Elder</a> and <a class="mtg-card-link" rel="#mtg-card-popup" href="http://gatherer.wizards.com/Handlers/Image.ashx?size=small&type=card&name=Solemn%20Simulacrum&options=" data-card="Solemn Simulacrum">Solemn Simulacrum</a>.  Second you need win conditions that are unaffected by the <a class="mtg-card-link" rel="#mtg-card-popup" href="http://gatherer.wizards.com/Handlers/Image.ashx?size=small&type=card&name=Death%20Match&options=" data-card="Death Match">Death Match</a>.  This either means spells or creatures it can&rsquo;t deal with.  This means creatures that are untargetable or have protection from black.  I found <a class="mtg-card-link" rel="#mtg-card-popup" href="http://gatherer.wizards.com/Handlers/Image.ashx?size=small&type=card&name=Gigapede&options=" data-card="Gigapede">Gigapede</a> to be the perfect choice here. but any untargetable fatty is fine.  <a class="mtg-card-link" rel="#mtg-card-popup" href="http://gatherer.wizards.com/Handlers/Image.ashx?size=small&type=card&name=Kodama%20of%20the%20North%20Tree&options=" data-card="Kodama of the North Tree">Kodama of the North Tree</a> or <a class="mtg-card-link" rel="#mtg-card-popup" href="http://gatherer.wizards.com/Handlers/Image.ashx?size=small&type=card&name=Multani,%20Maro-Sorcerer&options=" data-card="Multani, Maro-Sorcerer">Multani</a> are also great or you can go with <a class="mtg-card-link" rel="#mtg-card-popup" href="http://gatherer.wizards.com/Handlers/Image.ashx?size=small&type=card&name=Fireball&options=" data-card="Fireball">Fireball</a> or <a class="mtg-card-link" rel="#mtg-card-popup" href="http://gatherer.wizards.com/Handlers/Image.ashx?size=small&type=card&name=Consume%20Spirit&options=" data-card="Consume Spirit">Consume Spirit</a> or something.  Third you likely want to really be able to abuse the <a class="mtg-card-link" rel="#mtg-card-popup" href="http://gatherer.wizards.com/Handlers/Image.ashx?size=small&type=card&name=Death%20Match&options=" data-card="Death Match">Death Match</a>.  I went with <a class="mtg-card-link" rel="#mtg-card-popup" href="http://gatherer.wizards.com/Handlers/Image.ashx?size=small&type=card&name=Deranged%20Hermit&options=" data-card="Deranged Hermit">Deranged Hermit</a> and <a class="mtg-card-link" rel="#mtg-card-popup" href="http://gatherer.wizards.com/Handlers/Image.ashx?size=small&type=card&name=Squirrel%20Nest&options=" data-card="Squirrel Nest">Squirrel Nest</a>.  Any creature token producer would do fine here from <a class="mtg-card-link" rel="#mtg-card-popup" href="http://gatherer.wizards.com/Handlers/Image.ashx?size=small&type=card&name=Centaur%20Glade&options=" data-card="Centaur Glade">Centaur Glade</a> to <a class="mtg-card-link" rel="#mtg-card-popup" href="http://gatherer.wizards.com/Handlers/Image.ashx?size=small&type=card&name=Mobilization&options=" data-card="Mobilization">Mobilization</a>.  I do find it interesting that in my deck <a class="mtg-card-link" rel="#mtg-card-popup" href="http://gatherer.wizards.com/Handlers/Image.ashx?size=small&type=card&name=Deranged%20Hermit&options=" data-card="Deranged Hermit">Deranged Hermit</a> is more of a mass removal spell than a win condition (the tokens are generally gone in 1-2 turns).  The rest of the deck is really just utility (hopefully in creature form to keep the count high). The end result is that you rarely have anything worth targeting with the <a class="mtg-card-link" rel="#mtg-card-popup" href="http://gatherer.wizards.com/Handlers/Image.ashx?size=small&type=card&name=Death%20Match&options=" data-card="Death Match">Death Match</a> trigger but have plenty to trigger it with yourself.  When an opponent casts a creature he will more likely want to get rid of the other opponent&rsquo;s 3/3 than one of your 1/1 squirrel tokens.  When your opponent&rsquo;s have killed enough of each others creatures you should be far enough ahead that taking control of the game wont be too hard.  The thing I like most about <a class="mtg-card-link" rel="#mtg-card-popup" href="http://gatherer.wizards.com/Handlers/Image.ashx?size=small&type=card&name=Death%20Match&options=" data-card="Death Match">Death Match</a> isn&rsquo;t that it is good though.  It is that it can be a fun card from any side of the table.  It provides interaction which makes a game much more enjoyable regardless of who is winning.  I hope I didn&rsquo;t kill my deck by explaining it too much.</p>

<p>Some other types of cards that can provide this type of interaction are cards like the <a class="mtg-card-link" rel="#mtg-card-popup" href="http://gatherer.wizards.com/Handlers/Image.ashx?size=small&type=card&name=Wishmonger&options=" data-card="Wishmonger">mongers</a> from Masques.  Anyone can activate them and if you build your deck around one of them it should benefit you most and cause your opponents you use it against each other.  Cards like <a class="mtg-card-link" rel="#mtg-card-popup" href="http://gatherer.wizards.com/Handlers/Image.ashx?size=small&type=card&name=Fecundity&options=" data-card="Fecundity">Fecundity</a>, <a class="mtg-card-link" rel="#mtg-card-popup" href="http://gatherer.wizards.com/Handlers/Image.ashx?size=small&type=card&name=Cowardice&options=" data-card="Cowardice">Cowardice</a> and <a class="mtg-card-link" rel="#mtg-card-popup" href="http://gatherer.wizards.com/Handlers/Image.ashx?size=small&type=card&name=Death%20Pits%20of%20Rath&options=" data-card="Death Pits of Rath">Death Pits of Rath</a> also fit into this category.  Also there are also cards like <a class="mtg-card-link" rel="#mtg-card-popup" href="http://gatherer.wizards.com/Handlers/Image.ashx?size=small&type=card&name=Mana%20Flare&options=" data-card="Mana Flare">Mana Flare</a>, <a class="mtg-card-link" rel="#mtg-card-popup" href="http://gatherer.wizards.com/Handlers/Image.ashx?size=small&type=card&name=Furnace%20of%20Rath&options=" data-card="Furnace of Rath">Furnace of Rath</a>, and <a class="mtg-card-link" rel="#mtg-card-popup" href="http://gatherer.wizards.com/Handlers/Image.ashx?size=small&type=card&name=Infernal%20Genesis&options=" data-card="Infernal Genesis">Infernal Genesis</a> that are close to this type of card but are much harder to make sure that it benefits you more than your opponent.  These can be just as fun but also are much more dangerous and will cause you to lose as often as win you the game, if not even more so (like Dustin and <a class="mtg-card-link" rel="#mtg-card-popup" href="http://gatherer.wizards.com/Handlers/Image.ashx?size=small&type=card&name=Infernal%20Genesis&options=" data-card="Infernal Genesis">Infernal Genesis</a>).</p>

<p>Getting back to more traditional card advantage I want to discuss how a multiplayer control deck must be different to one made for duels.</p>

<p>In general a good control deck made for a duel plans to trade cards one for one with the opponent and use either card drawing or mass removal to gain enough card advantage to overwhelm the opponent.  We have already learned that in multiplayer there is no such thing as a one-for-one trade so this traditional strategy isn&rsquo;t possible (this is why permission decks suck in multiplayer).  We have already gone over the method of trying to make other players provide your card advantage by dealing with each others cards but what about dealing with them yourself?  They key is to pack as much card advantage as possible into your deck.  I&rsquo;m talking more than would be needed for a duel.  While something like 8 <a class="mtg-card-link" rel="#mtg-card-popup" href="http://gatherer.wizards.com/Handlers/Image.ashx?size=small&type=card&name=Wrath%20of%20God&options=" data-card="Wrath of God">Wrath effects</a> would be almost overkill in a Mono White Control deck built for a duel in a large multiplayer game you want more like 10-12.  In order to have enough card advantage to win you need to have enough to be ahead of all other players.  Lets look at what I think my most successful multiplayer deck I&rsquo;ve ever built looks like:</p>

<p><div class="mtg-card-deck"><h3 class="mtg-card-deck-title">Really Big Red</h3><div class="mtg-card-deck-content">
<div class="mtg-card-list"><h4>Lands (4)</h4><ul><li><a class="mtg-card-link" rel="#mtg-card-popup" href="http://gatherer.wizards.com/Handlers/Image.ashx?size=small&type=card&name=%3Cem%3E1%20Shivan%20Gorge&options=" data-card="&lt;em&gt;1 Shivan Gorge"><em>1 Shivan Gorge</a></li><li><a class="mtg-card-link" rel="#mtg-card-popup" href="http://gatherer.wizards.com/Handlers/Image.ashx?size=small&type=card&name=%3C/em%3E4%20Temple%20of%20the%20False%20God&options=" data-card="&lt;/em&gt;4 Temple of the False God"></em>4 Temple of the False God</a></li><li><a class="mtg-card-link" rel="#mtg-card-popup" href="http://gatherer.wizards.com/Handlers/Image.ashx?size=small&type=card&name=%3Cem%3E4%20Ghitu%20Encampment&options=" data-card="&lt;em&gt;4 Ghitu Encampment"><em>4 Ghitu Encampment</a></li><li><a class="mtg-card-link" rel="#mtg-card-popup" href="http://gatherer.wizards.com/Handlers/Image.ashx?size=small&type=card&name=%3C/em%3E15%20Mountain&options=" data-card="&lt;/em&gt;15 Mountain"></em>15 Mountain</a></li></ul></div>
<div class="mtg-card-list"><h4>Creatures (6)</h4><ul><li><a class="mtg-card-link" rel="#mtg-card-popup" href="http://gatherer.wizards.com/Handlers/Image.ashx?size=small&type=card&name=%3Cem%3E4%20Crater%20Hellion&options=" data-card="&lt;em&gt;4 Crater Hellion"><em>4 Crater Hellion</a></li><li><a class="mtg-card-link" rel="#mtg-card-popup" href="http://gatherer.wizards.com/Handlers/Image.ashx?size=small&type=card&name=%3C/em%3E4%20Flametongue%20Kavu&options=" data-card="&lt;/em&gt;4 Flametongue Kavu"></em>4 Flametongue Kavu</a></li><li><a class="mtg-card-link" rel="#mtg-card-popup" href="http://gatherer.wizards.com/Handlers/Image.ashx?size=small&type=card&name=%3Cem%3E4%20Arc-Slogger&options=" data-card="&lt;em&gt;4 Arc-Slogger"><em>4 Arc-Slogger</a></li><li><a class="mtg-card-link" rel="#mtg-card-popup" href="http://gatherer.wizards.com/Handlers/Image.ashx?size=small&type=card&name=%3C/em%3E4%20Viashino%20Heretic&options=" data-card="&lt;/em&gt;4 Viashino Heretic"></em>4 Viashino Heretic</a></li><li><a class="mtg-card-link" rel="#mtg-card-popup" href="http://gatherer.wizards.com/Handlers/Image.ashx?size=small&type=card&name=%3Cem%3E1%20Tahngarth,%20Talruum%20Hero&options=" data-card="&lt;em&gt;1 Tahngarth, Talruum Hero"><em>1 Tahngarth, Talruum Hero</a></li><li><a class="mtg-card-link" rel="#mtg-card-popup" href="http://gatherer.wizards.com/Handlers/Image.ashx?size=small&type=card&name=%3C/em%3E4%20Shivan%20Hellkite&options=" data-card="&lt;/em&gt;4 Shivan Hellkite"></em>4 Shivan Hellkite</a></li></ul></div>
<div class="mtg-card-list"><h4>Spells (4)</h4><ul><li><a class="mtg-card-link" rel="#mtg-card-popup" href="http://gatherer.wizards.com/Handlers/Image.ashx?size=small&type=card&name=%3Cem%3E4%20Seal%20of%20Fire&options=" data-card="&lt;em&gt;4 Seal of Fire"><em>4 Seal of Fire</a></li><li><a class="mtg-card-link" rel="#mtg-card-popup" href="http://gatherer.wizards.com/Handlers/Image.ashx?size=small&type=card&name=%3C/em%3E4%20Starstorm&options=" data-card="&lt;/em&gt;4 Starstorm"></em>4 Starstorm</a></li><li><a class="mtg-card-link" rel="#mtg-card-popup" href="http://gatherer.wizards.com/Handlers/Image.ashx?size=small&type=card&name=%3Cem%3E4%20Violent%20Eruption&options=" data-card="&lt;em&gt;4 Violent Eruption"><em>4 Violent Eruption</a></li><li><a class="mtg-card-link" rel="#mtg-card-popup" href="http://gatherer.wizards.com/Handlers/Image.ashx?size=small&type=card&name=%3C/em%3E3%20Rolling%20Thunder&options=" data-card="&lt;/em&gt;3 Rolling Thunder"></em>3 Rolling Thunder</a></li></ul></div>
</div></div></p>

<p>This is what I think is the optimal build of the deck (subject to change).  Another land might be nice but I&rsquo;m not sure what I&rsquo;d pull (probably a Heretic).</p>

<p>Look at the non-land cards in the deck.  How many of them can provide card advantage?  Every one of them but <a class="mtg-card-link" rel="#mtg-card-popup" href="http://gatherer.wizards.com/Handlers/Image.ashx?size=small&type=card&name=Seal%20of%20Fire&options=" data-card="Seal of Fire">Seal of Fire</a> can provide you with card advantage.  Even that one can provide virtual card advantage by holding off a few small attackers.  Earlier versions of the deck were based more on getting huge amounts of mana with card like <a class="mtg-card-link" rel="#mtg-card-popup" href="http://gatherer.wizards.com/Handlers/Image.ashx?size=small&type=card&name=Seething%20Song&options=" data-card="Seething Song">Seething Song</a>, <a class="mtg-card-link" rel="#mtg-card-popup" href="http://gatherer.wizards.com/Handlers/Image.ashx?size=small&type=card&name=Gilded%20Lotus&options=" data-card="Gilded Lotus">Gilded Lotus</a>, and <a class="mtg-card-link" rel="#mtg-card-popup" href="http://gatherer.wizards.com/Handlers/Image.ashx?size=small&type=card&name=Thawing%20Glaciers&options=" data-card="Thawing Glaciers">Thawing Glaciers</a> to power out huge spells.  I slowly ended up weeding out the mana producers one by one for more card advantage.  I haven&rsquo;t missed them yet but the deck hasn&rsquo;t had much testing since <a class="mtg-card-link" rel="#mtg-card-popup" href="http://gatherer.wizards.com/Handlers/Image.ashx?size=small&type=card&name=Gilded%20Lotus&options=" data-card="Gilded Lotus">Gilded Lotus</a> and <a class="mtg-card-link" rel="#mtg-card-popup" href="http://gatherer.wizards.com/Handlers/Image.ashx?size=small&type=card&name=Seething%20Song&options=" data-card="Seething Song">Seething Song</a> left.  I had noticed while Seething Song was great for a turn three <a class="mtg-card-link" rel="#mtg-card-popup" href="http://gatherer.wizards.com/Handlers/Image.ashx?size=small&type=card&name=Gilded%20Lotus&options=" data-card="Gilded Lotus">Gilded Lotus</a> or <a class="mtg-card-link" rel="#mtg-card-popup" href="http://gatherer.wizards.com/Handlers/Image.ashx?size=small&type=card&name=Arc-Slogger&options=" data-card="Arc-Slogger">Arc-Slogger</a> it was generally the card I least wanted to see at any other time.  After those went I decided that <a class="mtg-card-link" rel="#mtg-card-popup" href="http://gatherer.wizards.com/Handlers/Image.ashx?size=small&type=card&name=Gilded%20Lotus&options=" data-card="Gilded Lotus">Gilded Lotus</a> was now too slow as by turn 4-5 I&rsquo;d rather be playing threats and answers than getting more mana.  It hasn&rsquo;t been a problem yet but the deck likely has a higher chance of being mana screwed without them.</p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[Multiplayer Strategies]]></title>
    <link href="http://www.spekkionu.com/2005/05/multiplayer-strategies/"/>
    <updated>2005-05-11T14:06:52-07:00</updated>
    <id>http://www.spekkionu.com/2005/05/multiplayer-strategies</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>Often strategies that work in duels are quite terrible in multiplayer.  Something like a red land destruction deck stands no chance at all against multiple opponents since there will never be enough <a class="mtg-card-link" rel="#mtg-card-popup" href="http://gatherer.wizards.com/Handlers/Image.ashx?size=small&type=card&name=Stone%20Rain&options=" data-card="Stone Rain">Stone Rains</a> to keep everyone hurting for mana.  There are also strategies that are terrible in duels but gain a lot of power in multiplayer. This article will go over some strategies of each type as well as some general multiplayer strategy and deckbuilding advice.</p>

<!--more-->


<p>First I would recommend you get familiar with <a href="http://www.wizards.com/default.asp?x=mtgcom/daily/aa90">the terminology Anthony Alongi uses to categorize multiplayer cards</a>.  I&rsquo;ll paste his descriptions here:</p>

<p><strong>Rattlesnake cards warn off predators and redirect attention</strong><br/>
Think of how you react when an opponent plays <a class="mtg-card-link" rel="#mtg-card-popup" href="http://gatherer.wizards.com/Handlers/Image.ashx?size=small&type=card&name=Thrashing%20Wumpus&options=" data-card="Thrashing Wumpus">Thrashing Wumpus</a> and all you have are 1/1 creatures. Chances are, you&rsquo;re heading somewhere else.</p>

<p><strong>Gorilla cards smash the board and gain massive card advantage in one punch</strong><br/>
The easiest cards to notice, like <a class="mtg-card-link" rel="#mtg-card-popup" href="http://gatherer.wizards.com/Handlers/Image.ashx?size=small&type=card&name=Obliterate&options=" data-card="Obliterate">Obliterate</a> or <a class="mtg-card-link" rel="#mtg-card-popup" href="http://gatherer.wizards.com/Handlers/Image.ashx?size=small&type=card&name=Rout&options=" data-card="Rout">Rout</a></p>

<p><strong>Spider cards surprise opponents into making foolish choices, and gain card advantage by setting traps.</strong><br/>
An example here would be <a class="mtg-card-link" rel="#mtg-card-popup" href="http://gatherer.wizards.com/Handlers/Image.ashx?size=small&type=card&name=Spinal%20Embrace&options=" data-card="Spinal Embrace">Spinal Embrace</a>.</p>

<p><strong>Pigeon cards benefit directly from having more players on the board.</strong><br/>
Think of <a class="mtg-card-link" rel="#mtg-card-popup" href="http://gatherer.wizards.com/Handlers/Image.ashx?size=small&type=card&name=Syphon%20Soul&options=" data-card="Syphon Soul">Syphon Soul</a> or <a class="mtg-card-link" rel="#mtg-card-popup" href="http://gatherer.wizards.com/Handlers/Image.ashx?size=small&type=card&name=Syphon%20Mind&options=" data-card="Syphon Mind">Syphon Mind</a>.</p>

<p><strong>Plankton cards allow multiple players to participate, and feel a bit like a feeding ground</strong><br/>
Along the lines of <a class="mtg-card-link" rel="#mtg-card-popup" href="http://gatherer.wizards.com/Handlers/Image.ashx?size=small&type=card&name=Awakening&options=" data-card="Awakening">Awakening</a> or <a class="mtg-card-link" rel="#mtg-card-popup" href="http://gatherer.wizards.com/Handlers/Image.ashx?size=small&type=card&name=Wishmonger&options=" data-card="Wishmonger">Wishmonger</a>.</p>

<p><strong>Cockroach cards have persistent, repeatable effects that just keep showing up in the game.</strong><br/>
<a class="mtg-card-link" rel="#mtg-card-popup" href="http://gatherer.wizards.com/Handlers/Image.ashx?size=small&type=card&name=Flood&options=" data-card="Flood">Flood</a>, <a class="mtg-card-link" rel="#mtg-card-popup" href="http://gatherer.wizards.com/Handlers/Image.ashx?size=small&type=card&name=Masticore&options=" data-card="Masticore">Masticore</a>, and <a class="mtg-card-link" rel="#mtg-card-popup" href="http://gatherer.wizards.com/Handlers/Image.ashx?size=small&type=card&name=Genesis&options=" data-card="Genesis">Genesis</a> are the sorts of cards that drive the rest of the table buggy.</p>

<h2>Multiplayer Myths:</h2>

<p>I now want to talk about a couple of mistakes people make in their multiplayer strategies.</p>

<h3>Look helpless or you will be ganged up on:</h3>

<p>One thing I&rsquo;ve read in many articles and have seen in forums is the belief that the best multiplayer deck is one that looks helpless for most of the game and then tries to surprise everyone and win suddenly.  They say if you look helpless people will ignore you.  This is completely false.  Let&rsquo;s say you are playing a four player multiplayer game.  It is your turn and you have a <a class="mtg-card-link" rel="#mtg-card-popup" href="http://gatherer.wizards.com/Handlers/Image.ashx?size=small&type=card&name=Diving%20Griffin&options=" data-card="Diving Griffin">Diving Griffin</a> that you played last turn.  The second player has out a <a class="mtg-card-link" rel="#mtg-card-popup" href="http://gatherer.wizards.com/Handlers/Image.ashx?size=small&type=card&name=Seal%20of%20Fire&options=" data-card="Seal of Fire">Seal of Fire</a>.  Player three has <a class="mtg-card-link" rel="#mtg-card-popup" href="http://gatherer.wizards.com/Handlers/Image.ashx?size=small&type=card&name=Wall%20of%20Air&options=" data-card="Wall of Air">Wall of Air</a> and the fourth player has nothing.  Who do you attack?  Attacking player 2 will likely cost you your creature and not get any damage through.  Clearly not the best option.  Attacking player 3 will accomplish nothing as your creature will just bounce off his wall.  Of course you will go for the player with nothing out.  This goes directly against the belief that people will ignore someone that looks helpless.</p>

<h3>The early game isn&rsquo;t important in multiplayer:</h3>

<p>This is slightly related to the last point but isn&rsquo;t exactly the same thing.  In some groups anyone who attacks during the early turns are looked down upon.  While this makes no sense to me and likely doesn&rsquo;t to any of you I&rsquo;ve actually seen this in action on Magic Online.  In some of the types of multiplayer on there if you don&rsquo;t just spend your first three turns playing things like <a class="mtg-card-link" rel="#mtg-card-popup" href="http://gatherer.wizards.com/Handlers/Image.ashx?size=small&type=card&name=Llanowar%20Elves&options=" data-card="Llanowar Elves">Llanowar Elves</a>, <a class="mtg-card-link" rel="#mtg-card-popup" href="http://gatherer.wizards.com/Handlers/Image.ashx?size=small&type=card&name=Wild%20Growth&options=" data-card="Wild Growth">Wild Growth</a>, and <a class="mtg-card-link" rel="#mtg-card-popup" href="http://gatherer.wizards.com/Handlers/Image.ashx?size=small&type=card&name=Sakura-Tribe%20Elder&options=" data-card="Sakura-Tribe Elder">Sakura-Tribe Elder</a> you are some kind of jerk who shouldn&rsquo;t be allowed to play multiplayer.  This is especially true in the Emperor format which has the most retarded magic players known to man.  Literally 80% of the emperor decks on Magic Online run green.  Every single game is exactly the same.  The Emperor casts a much mana acceleration as he can on the first turn while the flanks cast <a class="mtg-card-link" rel="#mtg-card-popup" href="http://gatherer.wizards.com/Handlers/Image.ashx?size=small&type=card&name=Wild%20Growth&options=" data-card="Wild Growth">Wild Growth</a> and <a class="mtg-card-link" rel="#mtg-card-popup" href="http://gatherer.wizards.com/Handlers/Image.ashx?size=small&type=card&name=Fertile%20Ground&options=" data-card="Fertile Ground">Fertile Ground</a> on the Emperor&rsquo;s lands (actually all on the same land).  On turn two the Emperor uses <a class="mtg-card-link" rel="#mtg-card-popup" href="http://gatherer.wizards.com/Handlers/Image.ashx?size=small&type=card&name=Early%20Harvest&options=" data-card="Early Harvest">Early Harvest</a> and occasionally <a class="mtg-card-link" rel="#mtg-card-popup" href="http://gatherer.wizards.com/Handlers/Image.ashx?size=small&type=card&name=Heartbeat%20of%20Spring&options=" data-card="Heartbeat of Spring">Heartbeat of Spring</a> to generate as much mana as he can and casts the biggest <a class="mtg-card-link" rel="#mtg-card-popup" href="http://gatherer.wizards.com/Handlers/Image.ashx?size=small&type=card&name=New%20Frontiers&options=" data-card="New Frontiers">New Frontiers</a> he can.  On turn three the Emperor uses the insane amount of mana he now has to cast an enormous <a class="mtg-card-link" rel="#mtg-card-popup" href="http://gatherer.wizards.com/Handlers/Image.ashx?size=small&type=card&name=Weird%20Harvest&options=" data-card="Weird Harvest">Weird Harvest</a> (generally for 20+).  The flanks then cast all those creatures they found and win the game in one attack phase.  This was fun to watch once but when you realize that every single game ever plays out in the exact same fashion it you have to wonder how it can still be fun after the third game.  The proof is in the price of Online versions of <a class="mtg-card-link" rel="#mtg-card-popup" href="http://gatherer.wizards.com/Handlers/Image.ashx?size=small&type=card&name=New%20Frontiers&options=" data-card="New Frontiers">New Frontiers</a> (which is a crap rare in paper magic).  <a href="http://www.cardshark.com/magic/card_detail.asp?card_id=17405">Price of paper New Frontiers</a> = between $0.50 and $1.00.  <a href="http://www.cardshark.com/mtgo/card_detail.asp?card_id=17405">Price of online New Frontiers</a> = between $15.00 and $20.00.  A foil one will run you $100.  You could get a <a class="mtg-card-link" rel="#mtg-card-popup" href="http://gatherer.wizards.com/Handlers/Image.ashx?size=small&type=card&name=Mana%20Drain&options=" data-card="Mana Drain">Mana Drain</a> for that price.  That was a bit of a random rant but the point is that the early game is just as important in multiplayer as in a duel.  Your multiplayer deck should be capable of being able to fight off some early disruption/beats and hopefully provide some of your own.</p>

<h3>Card advantage is not important in multiplayer:</h3>

<p>Card advantage in multiplayer in some ways is harder to get than in a duel and in other ways much easier.  A card like <a class="mtg-card-link" rel="#mtg-card-popup" href="http://gatherer.wizards.com/Handlers/Image.ashx?size=small&type=card&name=Concentrate&options=" data-card="Concentrate">Concentrate</a> that gives you a few cards wont have quite the effect it has in a duel.  That isn&rsquo;t to say that drawing extra cards isn&rsquo;t good but generally a slower but more constant source of extra cards is more helpful in a multiplayer game.  On the other side of card advantage is mass removal.  This gets even better as with more players you are generally blowing up more stuff.  Control decks need more ways of getting card advantage as they can&rsquo;t just trade one-for-one for most of the game and cast a few card drawing spells to stay ahead.  There are just too many threats to be able to answer them one at a time.  This is the major reason why permission decks get weaker the more players there are.  <a class="mtg-card-link" rel="#mtg-card-popup" href="http://gatherer.wizards.com/Handlers/Image.ashx?size=small&type=card&name=Counterspell&options=" data-card="Counterspell">Counterspell</a> only nullifies one threat and you will have neither the mana nor the cards to answer all of them.  You want as many of your answers to provide card advantage as possible.  This doesn&rsquo;t just mean <a class="mtg-card-link" rel="#mtg-card-popup" href="http://gatherer.wizards.com/Handlers/Image.ashx?size=small&type=card&name=Wrath%20of%20God&options=" data-card="Wrath of God">Wrath of God</a> type effects.  Burn that lets you split up the damage like <a class="mtg-card-link" rel="#mtg-card-popup" href="http://gatherer.wizards.com/Handlers/Image.ashx?size=small&type=card&name=Fire%20//%20Ice&options=" data-card="Fire // Ice">Fire // Ice</a> and <a class="mtg-card-link" rel="#mtg-card-popup" href="http://gatherer.wizards.com/Handlers/Image.ashx?size=small&type=card&name=Pyrotechnics&options=" data-card="Pyrotechnics">Pyrotechnics</a> or reusable removal like <a class="mtg-card-link" rel="#mtg-card-popup" href="http://gatherer.wizards.com/Handlers/Image.ashx?size=small&type=card&name=Kumano,%20Master%20Yamabushi&options=" data-card="Kumano, Master Yamabushi">Kumano</a> or <a class="mtg-card-link" rel="#mtg-card-popup" href="http://gatherer.wizards.com/Handlers/Image.ashx?size=small&type=card&name=Tahngarth,%20Talruum%20Hero&options=" data-card="Tahngarth, Talruum Hero">Tahngarth</a> can often dominate a game.  The path to card advantage is more often re-usability rather than just trying to get two-for-ones.</p>

<h3>Lifegain is unbeatable in multiplayer:</h3>

<p>Just because you gained 64 life off a <a class="mtg-card-link" rel="#mtg-card-popup" href="http://gatherer.wizards.com/Handlers/Image.ashx?size=small&type=card&name=Congregate&options=" data-card="Congregate">Congregate</a> doesn&rsquo;t mean the game will go your way.  There is practically no limit to the amount of damage the table can deal if they all go after one person.  Once that life total gets above 30 you may find yourself with much more attention than you wanted.  I&rsquo;ve never advocated trying to appear helpless to get a surprise win but there is also going too far the other way and pissing off the entire table.  With enough people gunning for you even a 200+ life total wont save you.</p>

<h2>Duel strategies that don&rsquo;t work well in multiplayer:</h2>

<h3>Land Destruction:</h3>

<p>Land destruction can be very effective in a duel.  These decks seek to keep an opponent from having enough mana for his deck to perform correctly.  In multiplayer cards like <a class="mtg-card-link" rel="#mtg-card-popup" href="http://gatherer.wizards.com/Handlers/Image.ashx?size=small&type=card&name=Stone%20Rain&options=" data-card="Stone Rain">Stone Rain</a> and <a class="mtg-card-link" rel="#mtg-card-popup" href="http://gatherer.wizards.com/Handlers/Image.ashx?size=small&type=card&name=Rain%20of%20Tears&options=" data-card="Rain of Tears">Rain of Tears</a> lose their effectiveness as they only effect one person.  Sure you may be able to mana screw one person but nothing will stop the other three from killing you.  The exception to this is of course mass land removal like <a class="mtg-card-link" rel="#mtg-card-popup" href="http://gatherer.wizards.com/Handlers/Image.ashx?size=small&type=card&name=Armageddon&options=" data-card="Armageddon">Armageddon</a>, <a class="mtg-card-link" rel="#mtg-card-popup" href="http://gatherer.wizards.com/Handlers/Image.ashx?size=small&type=card&name=Wildfire&options=" data-card="Wildfire">Wildfire</a>, and <a class="mtg-card-link" rel="#mtg-card-popup" href="http://gatherer.wizards.com/Handlers/Image.ashx?size=small&type=card&name=Catastrophe&options=" data-card="Catastrophe">Catastrophe</a>.  These however can make quite a few players unhappy as sometimes an <a class="mtg-card-link" rel="#mtg-card-popup" href="http://gatherer.wizards.com/Handlers/Image.ashx?size=small&type=card&name=Armageddon&options=" data-card="Armageddon">Armageddon</a> tends to add at least another hour to the game.  Some people like to be home before 3 AM.</p>

<h3>Permission:</h3>

<p>Permission decks rely on card advantage to win the game.  The permission itself is just a one-for-one answer to whatever spell the opponent is casting.  It is the card drawing that provides the card advantage these decks need to win.  There is no way you could find the mana or space for the amount of card drawing it would require to overcome multiple opponents with one-for-one answers.  The deck might work in a three player game but any more than that and you&rsquo;ll do nothing but piss people you can&rsquo;t stop off.  This isn&rsquo;t to say <a class="mtg-card-link" rel="#mtg-card-popup" href="http://gatherer.wizards.com/Handlers/Image.ashx?size=small&type=card&name=Counterspell&options=" data-card="Counterspell">Counterspell</a> is worthless in multiplayer.  It is still great for stopping a big threat or a board sweeper from ruining your day.  It just shouldn&rsquo;t be the focus of the deck.</p>

<h3>Combo decks that only kill one person:</h3>

<p><a href="http://www.germagic.de/nda/deck.php?id=548">Trix</a> was a broken combo deck.  However it would be quite crappy in a multiplayer game.  Sure it&rsquo;ll get rid of one person but what about the other three? This is true of not just combo decks but also aggro decks that tend to run out of gas shortly after they kill.  Cards like <a class="mtg-card-link" rel="#mtg-card-popup" href="http://gatherer.wizards.com/Handlers/Image.ashx?size=small&type=card&name=Ball%20Lightning&options=" data-card="Ball Lightning">Ball Lightning</a> might be amazing in duels but if the majority of your damage comes from temporary sources like that you likely will kill one or two people then have no chance against the rest.</p>

<h2>Good multiplayer strategies that don&rsquo;t work in duels:</h2>

<h3>Giant Dudes:</h3>

<p>Multiplayer is a good place to let Timmy free.  With so many people the games last long enough to build up the mana necessary to cast all of those 6+ casting spells that would never work in a duel.  With a decent mana engine you could even hardcast things like Myojin and <a class="mtg-card-link" rel="#mtg-card-popup" href="http://gatherer.wizards.com/Handlers/Image.ashx?size=small&type=card&name=Darksteel%20Colossus&options=" data-card="Darksteel Colossus">Darksteel Colossus</a>.  Besides being Timmy is fun.  Who doesn&rsquo;t like actually being able to cast something that costs 8 mana.</p>

<h3>Rattlesnake Cards:</h3>

<p>I&rsquo;m talking about cards like <a class="mtg-card-link" rel="#mtg-card-popup" href="http://gatherer.wizards.com/Handlers/Image.ashx?size=small&type=card&name=No%20Mercy&options=" data-card="No Mercy">No Mercy</a> that while aren&rsquo;t very good in a duel will keep opponents from attacking you.  Why attack the person who will wipe out your creatures rather than concentrate on the other people until you find that <a class="mtg-card-link" rel="#mtg-card-popup" href="http://gatherer.wizards.com/Handlers/Image.ashx?size=small&type=card&name=Disenchant&options=" data-card="Disenchant">Disenchant</a>?  For this reason it is even debatable whether <a class="mtg-card-link" rel="#mtg-card-popup" href="http://gatherer.wizards.com/Handlers/Image.ashx?size=small&type=card&name=Seal%20of%20Fire&options=" data-card="Seal of Fire">Seal of Fire</a> is better than <a class="mtg-card-link" rel="#mtg-card-popup" href="http://gatherer.wizards.com/Handlers/Image.ashx?size=small&type=card&name=Lightning%20Bolt&options=" data-card="Lightning Bolt">Lightning Bolt</a> in multiplayer.</p>

<h3>Pigeon Cards:</h3>

<p><a class="mtg-card-link" rel="#mtg-card-popup" href="http://gatherer.wizards.com/Handlers/Image.ashx?size=small&type=card&name=Syphon%20Mind&options=" data-card="Syphon Mind">Syphon Mind</a> is a bad card in duels.  It is basically just a cantrip discard spell.  Four mana to make your opponent discard one card of his choice is not a good deal at all.  However, in multiplayer It will provide much more card advantage.  With 4 opponents it causes the discard of 4 cards and lets you draw 4.  Drawing 4 cards for 4 mana is a good deal and the discard makes it even better.  Cards like <a class="mtg-card-link" rel="#mtg-card-popup" href="http://gatherer.wizards.com/Handlers/Image.ashx?size=small&type=card&name=Blatant%20Thievery&options=" data-card="Blatant Thievery">Blatant Thievery</a>, <a class="mtg-card-link" rel="#mtg-card-popup" href="http://gatherer.wizards.com/Handlers/Image.ashx?size=small&type=card&name=Lhurgoyf&options=" data-card="Lhurgoyf">Lhurgoyf</a>, <a class="mtg-card-link" rel="#mtg-card-popup" href="http://gatherer.wizards.com/Handlers/Image.ashx?size=small&type=card&name=Multani,%20Maro%20Sorcerer&options=" data-card="Multani, Maro Sorcerer">Multani</a>, <a class="mtg-card-link" rel="#mtg-card-popup" href="http://gatherer.wizards.com/Handlers/Image.ashx?size=small&type=card&name=Verdant%20Force&options=" data-card="Verdant Force">Verdant Force</a>, and <a class="mtg-card-link" rel="#mtg-card-popup" href="http://gatherer.wizards.com/Handlers/Image.ashx?size=small&type=card&name=Congregate&options=" data-card="Congregate">Congregate</a> also fall into this category.</p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[Building a Control Deck]]></title>
    <link href="http://www.spekkionu.com/2005/04/building-a-control-deck/"/>
    <updated>2005-04-27T16:13:58-07:00</updated>
    <id>http://www.spekkionu.com/2005/04/building-a-control-deck</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>This article will cover how to build a blue-based control deck, how to play it, and also how to play against one.  The examples will not only include Mono Blue Control but a couple of other blue heavy control decks as well.  Control decks form a very large and important part of our metagame so I feel it is important to understand them even if you don&rsquo;t want to actually build one.</p>

<!--more-->


<h2>Building the Deck:</h2>

<p>This deck is essentially just counterspells and card drawing with a couple of win conditions and answers to threats that sneak through permission.  The deck is actually quite easy to build.</p>

<h3>Land:</h3>

<p>MUC is a very mana hungry deck.  It doesn&rsquo;t like to miss land drops.  As such it runs more land than the average deck.  The best number is historically 26 lands.  This can be lowered if the deck runs many cheap cantrip effects but not very often.  This is one problem many people have building these decks.  They can&rsquo;t bring themselves to run this much land in any deck.  Most new players always stick 20 land in every deck regardless of what the mana curve looks like.  While the costs of most of the spells themselves in these decks isn&rsquo;t expensive you generally want to be able to cast more than one a turn.  You want to be able to draw cards and counter spells not choose between the two.</p>

<p>As for which lands to run man-lands are always great in a MUC deck, especially against other control decks.  Since the deck runs so much land you can afford some of it to be colorless.  You generally still want at least 18 of the lands to produce blue but the rest can be something with a useful ability.</p>

<h3>Countermagic:</h3>

<p>You want a lot.  Anywhere from 12-14 counterspells is desirable.  You want these counterspells to be as cheap as possible.  If at all possible avoid counters that cost 4 mana.  Cards like <a class="mtg-card-link" rel="#mtg-card-popup" href="http://gatherer.wizards.com/Handlers/Image.ashx?size=small&type=card&name=Rewind&options=" data-card="Rewind">Rewind</a> and <a class="mtg-card-link" rel="#mtg-card-popup" href="http://gatherer.wizards.com/Handlers/Image.ashx?size=small&type=card&name=Discombobulate&options=" data-card="Discombobulate">Discombobulate</a> are more often than not too expensive.  A counterspell is not very good if it costs more than the spell it is countering (the biggest reason why these decks have problems with fast weenie decks).  This of course means that <a class="mtg-card-link" rel="#mtg-card-popup" href="http://gatherer.wizards.com/Handlers/Image.ashx?size=small&type=card&name=Spell%20Blast&options=" data-card="Spell Blast">Spell Blast</a> is always terrible.</p>

<p>Needless to say a hard counter is better than a soft one.  Cards like <a class="mtg-card-link" rel="#mtg-card-popup" href="http://gatherer.wizards.com/Handlers/Image.ashx?size=small&type=card&name=Power%20Sink&options=" data-card="Power Sink">Power Sink</a> and <a class="mtg-card-link" rel="#mtg-card-popup" href="http://gatherer.wizards.com/Handlers/Image.ashx?size=small&type=card&name=Condescend&options=" data-card="Condescend">Condescend</a> are certainly not bad and can often make the deck if the pickings are slim (like in the current standard) but are not as good as cards like <a class="mtg-card-link" rel="#mtg-card-popup" href="http://gatherer.wizards.com/Handlers/Image.ashx?size=small&type=card&name=Counterspell&options=" data-card="Counterspell">Counterspell</a> and <a class="mtg-card-link" rel="#mtg-card-popup" href="http://gatherer.wizards.com/Handlers/Image.ashx?size=small&type=card&name=Dissipate&options=" data-card="Dissipate">Dissipate</a>.  The exception to this is <a class="mtg-card-link" rel="#mtg-card-popup" href="http://gatherer.wizards.com/Handlers/Image.ashx?size=small&type=card&name=Mana%20Leak&options=" data-card="Mana Leak">Mana Leak</a> which is very cheap and makes your opponent pay enough mana that you can&rsquo;t just play around it easily.  This is a pretty slim boundary though as while <a class="mtg-card-link" rel="#mtg-card-popup" href="http://gatherer.wizards.com/Handlers/Image.ashx?size=small&type=card&name=Mana%20Leak&options=" data-card="Mana Leak">Mana Leak</a> is great <a class="mtg-card-link" rel="#mtg-card-popup" href="http://gatherer.wizards.com/Handlers/Image.ashx?size=small&type=card&name=Miscalculation&options=" data-card="Miscalculation">Miscalculation</a> is terrible and that only makes your opponent pay one less mana and has cycling to make it not dead late when your opponent has enough mana to make it less useful.</p>

<p>I don&rsquo;t recommend using counters that only are useful in certain situations.  Cards like <a class="mtg-card-link" rel="#mtg-card-popup" href="http://gatherer.wizards.com/Handlers/Image.ashx?size=small&type=card&name=Remove%20Soul&options=" data-card="Remove Soul">Remove Soul</a> or <a class="mtg-card-link" rel="#mtg-card-popup" href="http://gatherer.wizards.com/Handlers/Image.ashx?size=small&type=card&name=Thoughtbind&options=" data-card="Thoughtbind">Thoughtbind</a> can sometimes be useful but often just don&rsquo;t work when you need them to.  Very few of these situational counterspells are playable let alone good.</p>

<p>I&rsquo;ll end this section with a top 10 list of counterspells starting with the best on down. Since this is for a mono-U list I&rsquo;m leaving multicolored cards out of it so no <a class="mtg-card-link" rel="#mtg-card-popup" href="http://gatherer.wizards.com/Handlers/Image.ashx?size=small&type=card&name=Undermine&options=" data-card="Undermine">Undermine</a> or other multicolored counterspells.</p>

<p><div class="mtg-card-deck"><div class="mtg-card-deck-content">
<div class="mtg-card-list"><ul><li><a class="mtg-card-link" rel="#mtg-card-popup" href="http://gatherer.wizards.com/Handlers/Image.ashx?size=small&type=card&name=Force%20of%20Will&options=" data-card="Force of Will">Force of Will</a></li><li><a class="mtg-card-link" rel="#mtg-card-popup" href="http://gatherer.wizards.com/Handlers/Image.ashx?size=small&type=card&name=Mana%20Drain&options=" data-card="Mana Drain">Mana Drain</a></li><li><a class="mtg-card-link" rel="#mtg-card-popup" href="http://gatherer.wizards.com/Handlers/Image.ashx?size=small&type=card&name=Counterspell&options=" data-card="Counterspell">Counterspell</a></li><li><a class="mtg-card-link" rel="#mtg-card-popup" href="http://gatherer.wizards.com/Handlers/Image.ashx?size=small&type=card&name=Mana%20Leak&options=" data-card="Mana Leak">Mana Leak</a></li><li><a class="mtg-card-link" rel="#mtg-card-popup" href="http://gatherer.wizards.com/Handlers/Image.ashx?size=small&type=card&name=Forbid&options=" data-card="Forbid">Forbid</a></li><li><a class="mtg-card-link" rel="#mtg-card-popup" href="http://gatherer.wizards.com/Handlers/Image.ashx?size=small&type=card&name=Dissipate&options=" data-card="Dissipate">Dissipate</a></li><li><a class="mtg-card-link" rel="#mtg-card-popup" href="http://gatherer.wizards.com/Handlers/Image.ashx?size=small&type=card&name=Daze&options=" data-card="Daze">Daze</a></li><li><a class="mtg-card-link" rel="#mtg-card-popup" href="http://gatherer.wizards.com/Handlers/Image.ashx?size=small&type=card&name=Foil&options=" data-card="Foil">Foil</a></li><li><a class="mtg-card-link" rel="#mtg-card-popup" href="http://gatherer.wizards.com/Handlers/Image.ashx?size=small&type=card&name=Dismiss&options=" data-card="Dismiss">Dismiss</a></li><li><a class="mtg-card-link" rel="#mtg-card-popup" href="http://gatherer.wizards.com/Handlers/Image.ashx?size=small&type=card&name=Hinder&options=" data-card="Hinder">Hinder</a></li></ul></div>
</div></div></p>

<p>The first four are by far the best and go in order from best to worst.  The rest of the list is more flexible though and are all at a similar power level.</p>

<h3>Card Drawing:</h3>

<p>Since counters only trade for a card one-for-one you need some way of always having them on hand without running out.  This is important and no MUC deck would work without this very important section.  Playing a MUC deck and not holding any countermagic is a very scary situation to be in as your opponent can pretty much do anything he wants.</p>

<p>There are two types of card drawing.  There is card selection and actual card drawing.  Both are nice to have and I&rsquo;ll go over them separately as it is important to make the distinction between the two.</p>

<p>Card Selection does not actually increase the size of your hand but still helps you find what you need.  These will help you improve the quality of your draws.  You can use them to find needed land in the early game or make sure you don&rsquo;t draw the land but instead actual relevant cards later on.  Tutors are also included in this section.  Never pay more than two mana for one of these as they don&rsquo;t actually give you card advantage and some are even card disadvantage (such as <a class="mtg-card-link" rel="#mtg-card-popup" href="http://gatherer.wizards.com/Handlers/Image.ashx?size=small&type=card&name=Mystical%20Tutor&options=" data-card="Mystical Tutor">Mystical Tutor</a>).  I&rsquo;ll list some of the better examples (in no particular order):</p>

<p><div class="mtg-card-deck"><div class="mtg-card-deck-content">
<div class="mtg-card-list"><ul><li><a class="mtg-card-link" rel="#mtg-card-popup" href="http://gatherer.wizards.com/Handlers/Image.ashx?size=small&type=card&name=Brainstorm&options=" data-card="Brainstorm">Brainstorm</a></li><li><a class="mtg-card-link" rel="#mtg-card-popup" href="http://gatherer.wizards.com/Handlers/Image.ashx?size=small&type=card&name=Serum%20Visions&options=" data-card="Serum Visions">Serum Visions</a></li><li><a class="mtg-card-link" rel="#mtg-card-popup" href="http://gatherer.wizards.com/Handlers/Image.ashx?size=small&type=card&name=Opt&options=" data-card="Opt">Opt</a></li><li><a class="mtg-card-link" rel="#mtg-card-popup" href="http://gatherer.wizards.com/Handlers/Image.ashx?size=small&type=card&name=Impulse&options=" data-card="Impulse">Impulse</a></li><li><a class="mtg-card-link" rel="#mtg-card-popup" href="http://gatherer.wizards.com/Handlers/Image.ashx?size=small&type=card&name=Peer%20through%20Depths&options=" data-card="Peer through Depths">Peer through Depths</a></li><li><a class="mtg-card-link" rel="#mtg-card-popup" href="http://gatherer.wizards.com/Handlers/Image.ashx?size=small&type=card&name=Merchant%20Scroll&options=" data-card="Merchant Scroll">Merchant Scroll</a></li><li><a class="mtg-card-link" rel="#mtg-card-popup" href="http://gatherer.wizards.com/Handlers/Image.ashx?size=small&type=card&name=Sleight%20of%20Hand&options=" data-card="Sleight of Hand">Sleight of Hand</a></li><li><a class="mtg-card-link" rel="#mtg-card-popup" href="http://gatherer.wizards.com/Handlers/Image.ashx?size=small&type=card&name=Mystical%20Tutor&options=" data-card="Mystical Tutor">Mystical Tutor</a></li><li><a class="mtg-card-link" rel="#mtg-card-popup" href="http://gatherer.wizards.com/Handlers/Image.ashx?size=small&type=card&name=Intuition&options=" data-card="Intuition">Intuition</a></li></ul></div>
</div></div></p>

<p>Once again I&rsquo;m sure I missed some important ones.  Everything on this list is pretty cheap so getting them wont be hard (with the exception of <a class="mtg-card-link" rel="#mtg-card-popup" href="http://gatherer.wizards.com/Handlers/Image.ashx?size=small&type=card&name=Intuition&options=" data-card="Intuition">Intuition</a>).  Also included in this category is pretty much any cantrip.</p>

<p>Actual card drawing is different.  In order to be in this category it has to actually increase the size of your hand.  While <a class="mtg-card-link" rel="#mtg-card-popup" href="http://gatherer.wizards.com/Handlers/Image.ashx?size=small&type=card&name=Brainstorm&options=" data-card="Brainstorm">Brainstorm</a> is easily the best card selection card ever printed it isn&rsquo;t actually card drawing.  If you have 4 cards in your hand and cast it you will still have 4 cards.  This is a card advantage of +0.  An example of actual card advantage would be casting <a class="mtg-card-link" rel="#mtg-card-popup" href="http://gatherer.wizards.com/Handlers/Image.ashx?size=small&type=card&name=Concentrate&options=" data-card="Concentrate">Concentrate</a>.  Starting with 4 cards in hand after you cast it you will have 6.  This is a card advantage of +2.  As good as some of the cards in the card selection section are you cannot built a good MUC deck without real card drawing that provides card advantage.  Without some of these you are guaranteed to run out of countermagic eventually and unless you opponent has a bad draw will likely be overrun by whatever gets through when you run out.  I&rsquo;ll list some actual card drawing (once again in no particular order):</p>

<p><div class="mtg-card-deck"><div class="mtg-card-deck-content">
<div class="mtg-card-list"><ul><li><a class="mtg-card-link" rel="#mtg-card-popup" href="http://gatherer.wizards.com/Handlers/Image.ashx?size=small&type=card&name=Concentrate&options=" data-card="Concentrate">Concentrate</a></li><li><a class="mtg-card-link" rel="#mtg-card-popup" href="http://gatherer.wizards.com/Handlers/Image.ashx?size=small&type=card&name=Counsel%20of%20the%20Soratami&options=" data-card="Counsel of the Soratami">Counsel of the Soratami</a></li><li><a class="mtg-card-link" rel="#mtg-card-popup" href="http://gatherer.wizards.com/Handlers/Image.ashx?size=small&type=card&name=Inspiration&options=" data-card="Inspiration">Inspiration</a></li><li><a class="mtg-card-link" rel="#mtg-card-popup" href="http://gatherer.wizards.com/Handlers/Image.ashx?size=small&type=card&name=Fact%20or%20Fiction&options=" data-card="Fact or Fiction">Fact or Fiction</a></li><li><a class="mtg-card-link" rel="#mtg-card-popup" href="http://gatherer.wizards.com/Handlers/Image.ashx?size=small&type=card&name=Thirst%20for%20Knowledge&options=" data-card="Thirst for Knowledge">Thirst for Knowledge</a></li><li><a class="mtg-card-link" rel="#mtg-card-popup" href="http://gatherer.wizards.com/Handlers/Image.ashx?size=small&type=card&name=Opportunity&options=" data-card="Opportunity">Opportunity</a></li><li><a class="mtg-card-link" rel="#mtg-card-popup" href="http://gatherer.wizards.com/Handlers/Image.ashx?size=small&type=card&name=Accumulated%20Knowledge&options=" data-card="Accumulated Knowledge">Accumulated Knowledge</a></li><li><a class="mtg-card-link" rel="#mtg-card-popup" href="http://gatherer.wizards.com/Handlers/Image.ashx?size=small&type=card&name=Braingeyser&options=" data-card="Braingeyser">Braingeyser</a></li><li><a class="mtg-card-link" rel="#mtg-card-popup" href="http://gatherer.wizards.com/Handlers/Image.ashx?size=small&type=card&name=Stroke%20of%20Genius&options=" data-card="Stroke of Genius">Stroke of Genius</a></li><li><a class="mtg-card-link" rel="#mtg-card-popup" href="http://gatherer.wizards.com/Handlers/Image.ashx?size=small&type=card&name=Deep%20Analysis&options=" data-card="Deep Analysis">Deep Analysis</a></li></ul></div>
</div></div></p>

<p>Unfortunately many of these are either bad (<a class="mtg-card-link" rel="#mtg-card-popup" href="http://gatherer.wizards.com/Handlers/Image.ashx?size=small&type=card&name=Inspiration&options=" data-card="Inspiration">Inspiration</a>), expensive (<a class="mtg-card-link" rel="#mtg-card-popup" href="http://gatherer.wizards.com/Handlers/Image.ashx?size=small&type=card&name=Opportunity&options=" data-card="Opportunity">Opportunity</a>), or sorcery speed (<a class="mtg-card-link" rel="#mtg-card-popup" href="http://gatherer.wizards.com/Handlers/Image.ashx?size=small&type=card&name=Concentrate&options=" data-card="Concentrate">Concentrate</a>).  This means that it is much harder to get some of the better ones.  If at all possible you want to avoid sorcery speed card drawing unless it only cards 1-2 mana (of which I can&rsquo;t think of any in blue anyway).  Unfortunately if you can&rsquo;t get a hold of the good ones you might just have to bite it and run a sorcery.  While this sucks Wizards has stated they don&rsquo;t want to print any more actual card drawing that isn&rsquo;t sorcery speed unless it is over costed (like <a class="mtg-card-link" rel="#mtg-card-popup" href="http://gatherer.wizards.com/Handlers/Image.ashx?size=small&type=card&name=Inspiration&options=" data-card="Inspiration">Inspiration</a>).  If you do run a sorcery don&rsquo;t cast it as soon as possible.  Wait until you can keep counter mana up.  This will take some of the sting out of it and makes some of these cards a bit better.</p>

<p>There is also another type of card drawing I should mention.  That is a drawing engine.  These are repeatable card drawing effects.  These can be creatures that let you draw cards when they hit or enchantments/artifacts that let you draw extra cards.  I&rsquo;ll give a list of some of these as well.</p>

<p><div class="mtg-card-deck"><div class="mtg-card-deck-content">
<div class="mtg-card-list"><ul><li><a class="mtg-card-link" rel="#mtg-card-popup" href="http://gatherer.wizards.com/Handlers/Image.ashx?size=small&type=card&name=Ophidian&options=" data-card="Ophidian">Ophidian</a></li><li><a class="mtg-card-link" rel="#mtg-card-popup" href="http://gatherer.wizards.com/Handlers/Image.ashx?size=small&type=card&name=Ninja%20of%20the%20Deep%20Hours&options=" data-card="Ninja of the Deep Hours">Ninja of the Deep Hours</a></li><li><a class="mtg-card-link" rel="#mtg-card-popup" href="http://gatherer.wizards.com/Handlers/Image.ashx?size=small&type=card&name=Thieving%20Magpie&options=" data-card="Thieving Magpie">Thieving Magpie</a></li><li><a class="mtg-card-link" rel="#mtg-card-popup" href="http://gatherer.wizards.com/Handlers/Image.ashx?size=small&type=card&name=Treasure%20Trove&options=" data-card="Treasure Trove">Treasure Trove</a></li><li><a class="mtg-card-link" rel="#mtg-card-popup" href="http://gatherer.wizards.com/Handlers/Image.ashx?size=small&type=card&name=Archivist&options=" data-card="Archivist">Archivist</a></li><li><a class="mtg-card-link" rel="#mtg-card-popup" href="http://gatherer.wizards.com/Handlers/Image.ashx?size=small&type=card&name=Jayemdae%20Tome&options=" data-card="Jayemdae Tome">Jayemdae Tome</a></li><li><a class="mtg-card-link" rel="#mtg-card-popup" href="http://gatherer.wizards.com/Handlers/Image.ashx?size=small&type=card&name=Planar%20Portal&options=" data-card="Planar Portal">Planar Portal</a></li><li><a class="mtg-card-link" rel="#mtg-card-popup" href="http://gatherer.wizards.com/Handlers/Image.ashx?size=small&type=card&name=Mind&rsquo;s%20Eye&options=" data-card="Mind&amp;rsquo;s Eye">Mind&rsquo;s Eye</a></li><li><a class="mtg-card-link" rel="#mtg-card-popup" href="http://gatherer.wizards.com/Handlers/Image.ashx?size=small&type=card&name=Arcanis%20the%20Omnipotent&options=" data-card="Arcanis the Omnipotent">Arcanis the Omnipotent</a></li><li><a class="mtg-card-link" rel="#mtg-card-popup" href="http://gatherer.wizards.com/Handlers/Image.ashx?size=small&type=card&name=Whispers%20of%20the%20Muse&options=" data-card="Whispers of the Muse">Whispers of the Muse</a></li></ul></div>
</div></div></p>

<p>You will want to run around 12 card drawing/selection cards total making sure at least 4 of them provide card advantage (preferable more like 8 of them if possible).  You want to value instants way above sorceries here and make sure all cards are as cheap as possible.  A draw engine is also very nice but usually not more than 4 (less if mana intensive).</p>

<h3>Win Condition:</h3>

<p>You have to win somehow.  These decks should run usually between 2-4 win conditions.  These can really be anything if the rest of the deck is made right but some are faster than others.  Usually a good fatty is the best for the job but cards like <a class="mtg-card-link" rel="#mtg-card-popup" href="http://gatherer.wizards.com/Handlers/Image.ashx?size=small&type=card&name=Millstone&options=" data-card="Millstone">Millstone</a> have also been used in the past.  Once again I&rsquo;ll provide a list:</p>

<p><div class="mtg-card-deck"><div class="mtg-card-deck-content">
<div class="mtg-card-list"><ul><li><a class="mtg-card-link" rel="#mtg-card-popup" href="http://gatherer.wizards.com/Handlers/Image.ashx?size=small&type=card&name=Mahamoti%20Djinn&options=" data-card="Mahamoti Djinn">Mahamoti Djinn</a></li><li><a class="mtg-card-link" rel="#mtg-card-popup" href="http://gatherer.wizards.com/Handlers/Image.ashx?size=small&type=card&name=Morphling&options=" data-card="Morphling">Morphling</a></li><li><a class="mtg-card-link" rel="#mtg-card-popup" href="http://gatherer.wizards.com/Handlers/Image.ashx?size=small&type=card&name=Air%20Elemental&options=" data-card="Air Elemental">Air Elemental</a></li><li><a class="mtg-card-link" rel="#mtg-card-popup" href="http://gatherer.wizards.com/Handlers/Image.ashx?size=small&type=card&name=Keiga,%20the%20Tide%20Star&options=" data-card="Keiga, the Tide Star">Keiga, the Tide Star</a></li><li><a class="mtg-card-link" rel="#mtg-card-popup" href="http://gatherer.wizards.com/Handlers/Image.ashx?size=small&type=card&name=Quicksilver%20Dragon&options=" data-card="Quicksilver Dragon">Quicksilver Dragon</a></li><li><a class="mtg-card-link" rel="#mtg-card-popup" href="http://gatherer.wizards.com/Handlers/Image.ashx?size=small&type=card&name=Zephid&options=" data-card="Zephid">Zephid</a></li><li><a class="mtg-card-link" rel="#mtg-card-popup" href="http://gatherer.wizards.com/Handlers/Image.ashx?size=small&type=card&name=Palinchron&options=" data-card="Palinchron">Palinchron</a></li><li><a class="mtg-card-link" rel="#mtg-card-popup" href="http://gatherer.wizards.com/Handlers/Image.ashx?size=small&type=card&name=Meloku%20the%20Clouded%20Mirror&options=" data-card="Meloku the Clouded Mirror">Meloku the Clouded Mirror</a></li><li><a class="mtg-card-link" rel="#mtg-card-popup" href="http://gatherer.wizards.com/Handlers/Image.ashx?size=small&type=card&name=Arcanis%20the%20Omnipotent&options=" data-card="Arcanis the Omnipotent">Arcanis the Omnipotent</a></li><li><a class="mtg-card-link" rel="#mtg-card-popup" href="http://gatherer.wizards.com/Handlers/Image.ashx?size=small&type=card&name=Rainbow%20Efreet&options=" data-card="Rainbow Efreet">Rainbow Efreet</a></li></ul></div>
</div></div></p>

<p>If you are running a large amount of man-lands you can actually get away without any creatures here but 1-2 is still a good idea just in case.</p>

<h3>Something to deal with threats that get through:</h3>

<p>No matter how much countermagic and card drawing you are running there is bound to be something that your opponent can force through.  These cards are here in order to deal with them.  Since blue has trouble dealing with permanents most of these tend to be artifacts.  Blue itself really only has two ways of doing this without artifacts.  The first is bounce.  This can be good especially repeatable bounce like <a class="mtg-card-link" rel="#mtg-card-popup" href="http://gatherer.wizards.com/Handlers/Image.ashx?size=small&type=card&name=Capsize&options=" data-card="Capsize">Capsize</a> or <a class="mtg-card-link" rel="#mtg-card-popup" href="http://gatherer.wizards.com/Handlers/Image.ashx?size=small&type=card&name=Temporal%20Adept&options=" data-card="Temporal Adept">Temporal Adept</a> but on average something that can actually permanently deal with the threat is better.  The second method is by stealing the threat.  Cards like <a class="mtg-card-link" rel="#mtg-card-popup" href="http://gatherer.wizards.com/Handlers/Image.ashx?size=small&type=card&name=Control%20Magic&options=" data-card="Control Magic">Control Magic</a> and <a class="mtg-card-link" rel="#mtg-card-popup" href="http://gatherer.wizards.com/Handlers/Image.ashx?size=small&type=card&name=Treachery&options=" data-card="Treachery">Treachery</a> are actually quite good as they not only deal with a threat but give you one as well.  This is basically another type of card advantage.  As for artifacts you can use things like <a class="mtg-card-link" rel="#mtg-card-popup" href="http://gatherer.wizards.com/Handlers/Image.ashx?size=small&type=card&name=Nevinyrral&rsquo;s%20Disk&options=" data-card="Nevinyrral&amp;rsquo;s Disk">Nevinyrral&rsquo;s Disk</a> or <a class="mtg-card-link" rel="#mtg-card-popup" href="http://gatherer.wizards.com/Handlers/Image.ashx?size=small&type=card&name=Powder%20Keg&options=" data-card="Powder Keg">Powder Keg</a> in order to deal with anything that slips through your wall of countermagic.  Here is the list:</p>

<p><div class="mtg-card-deck"><div class="mtg-card-deck-content">
<div class="mtg-card-list"><ul><li><a class="mtg-card-link" rel="#mtg-card-popup" href="http://gatherer.wizards.com/Handlers/Image.ashx?size=small&type=card&name=Nevinyrral&rsquo;s%20Disk&options=" data-card="Nevinyrral&amp;rsquo;s Disk">Nevinyrral&rsquo;s Disk</a></li><li><a class="mtg-card-link" rel="#mtg-card-popup" href="http://gatherer.wizards.com/Handlers/Image.ashx?size=small&type=card&name=Powder%20Keg&options=" data-card="Powder Keg">Powder Keg</a></li><li><a class="mtg-card-link" rel="#mtg-card-popup" href="http://gatherer.wizards.com/Handlers/Image.ashx?size=small&type=card&name=Engineered%20Explosives&options=" data-card="Engineered Explosives">Engineered Explosives</a></li><li><a class="mtg-card-link" rel="#mtg-card-popup" href="http://gatherer.wizards.com/Handlers/Image.ashx?size=small&type=card&name=Control%20Magic&options=" data-card="Control Magic">Control Magic</a></li><li><a class="mtg-card-link" rel="#mtg-card-popup" href="http://gatherer.wizards.com/Handlers/Image.ashx?size=small&type=card&name=Treachery&options=" data-card="Treachery">Treachery</a></li><li><a class="mtg-card-link" rel="#mtg-card-popup" href="http://gatherer.wizards.com/Handlers/Image.ashx?size=small&type=card&name=Vedalken%20Shackles&options=" data-card="Vedalken Shackles">Vedalken Shackles</a></li><li><a class="mtg-card-link" rel="#mtg-card-popup" href="http://gatherer.wizards.com/Handlers/Image.ashx?size=small&type=card&name=Legacy&rsquo;s%20Allure&options=" data-card="Legacy&amp;rsquo;s Allure">Legacy&rsquo;s Allure</a></li><li><a class="mtg-card-link" rel="#mtg-card-popup" href="http://gatherer.wizards.com/Handlers/Image.ashx?size=small&type=card&name=Temporal%20Adept&options=" data-card="Temporal Adept">Temporal Adept</a></li><li><a class="mtg-card-link" rel="#mtg-card-popup" href="http://gatherer.wizards.com/Handlers/Image.ashx?size=small&type=card&name=Time%20Elemental&options=" data-card="Time Elemental">Time Elemental</a></li><li><a class="mtg-card-link" rel="#mtg-card-popup" href="http://gatherer.wizards.com/Handlers/Image.ashx?size=small&type=card&name=Capsize&options=" data-card="Capsize">Capsize</a></li></ul></div>
</div></div></p>

<p>We now understand what goes into a MUC deck so let us now build one.  I&rsquo;m only going to use cheaper cards for this example so nothing like <a class="mtg-card-link" rel="#mtg-card-popup" href="http://gatherer.wizards.com/Handlers/Image.ashx?size=small&type=card&name=Intuition&options=" data-card="Intuition">Intuition</a>, <a class="mtg-card-link" rel="#mtg-card-popup" href="http://gatherer.wizards.com/Handlers/Image.ashx?size=small&type=card&name=Morphling&options=" data-card="Morphling">Morphling</a>, or <a class="mtg-card-link" rel="#mtg-card-popup" href="http://gatherer.wizards.com/Handlers/Image.ashx?size=small&type=card&name=Force%20of%20Will&options=" data-card="Force of Will">Force of Will</a>.</p>

<p><div class="mtg-card-deck"><h3 class="mtg-card-deck-title">Budget MUC</h3><div class="mtg-card-deck-content">
<div class="mtg-card-list"><h4>Lands (3)</h4><ul><li><a class="mtg-card-link" rel="#mtg-card-popup" href="http://gatherer.wizards.com/Handlers/Image.ashx?size=small&type=card&name=%3Cem%3E18%20Island&options=" data-card="&lt;em&gt;18 Island"><em>18 Island</a></li><li><a class="mtg-card-link" rel="#mtg-card-popup" href="http://gatherer.wizards.com/Handlers/Image.ashx?size=small&type=card&name=%3C/em%3E4%20Quicksand&options=" data-card="&lt;/em&gt;4 Quicksand"></em>4 Quicksand</a></li><li><a class="mtg-card-link" rel="#mtg-card-popup" href="http://gatherer.wizards.com/Handlers/Image.ashx?size=small&type=card&name=%3Cem%3E4%20Faerie%20Conclave&options=" data-card="&lt;em&gt;4 Faerie Conclave"><em>4 Faerie Conclave</a></li></ul></div>
<div class="mtg-card-list"><h4>Creatures (2)</h4><ul><li><a class="mtg-card-link" rel="#mtg-card-popup" href="http://gatherer.wizards.com/Handlers/Image.ashx?size=small&type=card&name=%3C/em%3E4%20Thieving%20Magpie&options=" data-card="&lt;/em&gt;4 Thieving Magpie"></em>4 Thieving Magpie</a></li><li><a class="mtg-card-link" rel="#mtg-card-popup" href="http://gatherer.wizards.com/Handlers/Image.ashx?size=small&type=card&name=%3Cem%3E2%20Mahamoti%20Djinn&options=" data-card="&lt;em&gt;2 Mahamoti Djinn"><em>2 Mahamoti Djinn</a></li></ul></div>
<div class="mtg-card-list"><h4>Spells (7)</h4><ul><li><a class="mtg-card-link" rel="#mtg-card-popup" href="http://gatherer.wizards.com/Handlers/Image.ashx?size=small&type=card&name=%3C/em%3E4%20Counterspell&options=" data-card="&lt;/em&gt;4 Counterspell"></em>4 Counterspell</a></li><li><a class="mtg-card-link" rel="#mtg-card-popup" href="http://gatherer.wizards.com/Handlers/Image.ashx?size=small&type=card&name=%3Cem%3E4%20Mana%20Leak&options=" data-card="&lt;em&gt;4 Mana Leak"><em>4 Mana Leak</a></li><li><a class="mtg-card-link" rel="#mtg-card-popup" href="http://gatherer.wizards.com/Handlers/Image.ashx?size=small&type=card&name=%3C/em%3E4%20Forbid&options=" data-card="&lt;/em&gt;4 Forbid"></em>4 Forbid</a></li><li><a class="mtg-card-link" rel="#mtg-card-popup" href="http://gatherer.wizards.com/Handlers/Image.ashx?size=small&type=card&name=%3Cem%3E4%20Dissipate&options=" data-card="&lt;em&gt;4 Dissipate"><em>4 Dissipate</a></li><li><a class="mtg-card-link" rel="#mtg-card-popup" href="http://gatherer.wizards.com/Handlers/Image.ashx?size=small&type=card&name=%3C/em%3E4%20Impulse&options=" data-card="&lt;/em&gt;4 Impulse"></em>4 Impulse</a></li><li><a class="mtg-card-link" rel="#mtg-card-popup" href="http://gatherer.wizards.com/Handlers/Image.ashx?size=small&type=card&name=%3Cem%3E4%20Accumulated%20Knowledge&options=" data-card="&lt;em&gt;4 Accumulated Knowledge"><em>4 Accumulated Knowledge</a></li><li><a class="mtg-card-link" rel="#mtg-card-popup" href="http://gatherer.wizards.com/Handlers/Image.ashx?size=small&type=card&name=%3C/em%3E4%20Control%20Magic&options=" data-card="&lt;/em&gt;4 Control Magic"></em>4 Control Magic</a></li></ul></div>
</div></div></p>

<p>This deck is actually quite cheap.  I went ahead and calculated the price of the deck if your were to purchase everything but the basic land.  So if did not own a single card in the deck other than Island on <a href="http://www.starcitygames.com/magic.php">Starcity</a> you would spend a total of $40.75 plus shipping.  This may sound a bit steep but take any deck you have and throw it in the deck builder and I can almost guarantee it will be higher.  Just to show how much better it is to buy cards on <a href="http://www.cardshark.com/">cardshark</a> I also calculated the price of buying the cards there.  It came to $16.49 plus shipping.  Once again buy cards from cardshark.  It is cheaper than ebay.  The deck could of course be made better by adding some more expensive cards like <a class="mtg-card-link" rel="#mtg-card-popup" href="http://gatherer.wizards.com/Handlers/Image.ashx?size=small&type=card&name=Fact%20or%20Fiction&options=" data-card="Fact or Fiction">Fact or Fiction</a> and <a class="mtg-card-link" rel="#mtg-card-popup" href="http://gatherer.wizards.com/Handlers/Image.ashx?size=small&type=card&name=Nevinyrral&rsquo;s%20Disk&options=" data-card="Nevinyrral&amp;rsquo;s Disk">Nevinyrral&rsquo;s Disk</a> but this version is still not bad at all and would be plenty strong for our environment.</p>

<h2>Playing the Deck:</h2>

<p>Now that we have covered how to build a MUC deck I&rsquo;ll go over how to play it.</p>

<p>MUC is a pure reactive deck.  Until you drop that win condition at the end of the game you pretty much do nothing but react to your opponent.  Even against other control decks the answer to the question <a href="http://www.starcitygames.com/php/news/expandnews.php?Article=3692">Who&rsquo;s the Beatdown?</a> is never you.  This is the most control you can get and pretty much everything will be the beatdown against you.  I&rsquo;ll now go over some general rules and tips for playing MUC.</p>

<p><strong>Rule #1:</strong> Never Tap Out.</p>

<p>Sometimes this is impossible to avoid but the key is to only do it when you have to.  Say on turn 4 you just played land number 4 and are holding <a class="mtg-card-link" rel="#mtg-card-popup" href="http://gatherer.wizards.com/Handlers/Image.ashx?size=small&type=card&name=Thieving%20Magpie&options=" data-card="Thieving Magpie">Thieving Magpie</a>.  Unless you are absolutely sure your opponent will not cast anything important next turn or are holding an alternate casting cost counterspell do not drop the creature.  You want to hold it until you can cast it and still keep mana open for countering.  This is true even if you are not holding a counterspell.  This also counts for casting sorcery speed card drawing and pretty much anything else during your turn.</p>

<p><strong>Rule #2:</strong> You are always holding the counterspell.</p>

<p>This is related to the previous rule.  Even if you are holding no countermagic you want to act like you are.  The absolute worst thing that could happen is for your opponent to know you can&rsquo;t counter something.  This will cause him to drop whatever nasty thing he can.  If he still thinks you can counter he may hold back on his most important spells perhaps hoping to weed out your counter magic with something less important.</p>

<p><strong>Rule #3:</strong> You are always in control.</p>

<p>This one continues that train of thought.  Even if it looks like you are in a loosing position acting like you have the answer can often cause your opponent to belive that and make them either make mistakes or play too defensively giving you time to actually draw the answer.</p>

<p><strong>Rule #4:</strong> Never counter something that isn&rsquo;t a threat.</p>

<p>If your opponent cast something you don&rsquo;t care about don&rsquo;t waste a counterspell on it.  You don&rsquo;t need to counter everything, just the things that may cause problems.  It is perfectly fine to ignore that <a class="mtg-card-link" rel="#mtg-card-popup" href="http://gatherer.wizards.com/Handlers/Image.ashx?size=small&type=card&name=Steel%20Wall&options=" data-card="Steel Wall">Steel Wall</a>, it isn&rsquo;t going to do anything.  You don&rsquo;t want to run out of countermagic before your opponent runs out of threats.  If you are running things like <a class="mtg-card-link" rel="#mtg-card-popup" href="http://gatherer.wizards.com/Handlers/Image.ashx?size=small&type=card&name=Nevinyrral&rsquo;s%20Disk&options=" data-card="Nevinyrral&amp;rsquo;s Disk">Nev&rsquo;s Disk</a> you can also ignore a few creatures as you can just blow them up later.  Remember only the last life point matters so don&rsquo;t worry about taking some early damage.  As such it usually is fine to not counter most burn unless it is huge or you are running low on life.</p>

<p><strong>Rule #5:</strong> Wait until the last possible time to do anything.</p>

<p>In general the longer you wait to do something the better.  Waiting means keeping your mana untapped which is better for both bluffing countermagic and keeping your options open.  Only cast instant card drawing at the end of your opponent&rsquo;s turn in order to minimize your vulnerability.  If you play that <a class="mtg-card-link" rel="#mtg-card-popup" href="http://gatherer.wizards.com/Handlers/Image.ashx?size=small&type=card&name=Thieving%20Magpie&options=" data-card="Thieving Magpie">Thieving Magpie</a> during your own turn then you will have 4 less mana to counter spells during your opponent&rsquo;s turn.  They will know this and may be able to get something through.</p>

<h2>Adding Another Color</h2>

<p>This is where I&rsquo;ll go over each other color and what they could add to the blue-heavy control deck.  I&rsquo;ll talk about the types of things they can help with and give an example in those colors.  I&rsquo;m not going to go into near as much detail as the mono-blue version though.  It&rsquo;ll just be a little explanation and a decklist.  The multi-color permission decks are actually don&rsquo;t play all that different to the mono-blue ones.  They just lose a bit of mana consistency and permission density for the ability to do a few extra things blue can&rsquo;t do on its own.</p>

<h3>Black:</h3>

<p>Black has quite a bit to offer the blue mage.  The first and possibly most powerful is discard.  Discard is a way to proactively deal with threats.  Something like <a class="mtg-card-link" rel="#mtg-card-popup" href="http://gatherer.wizards.com/Handlers/Image.ashx?size=small&type=card&name=Duress&options=" data-card="Duress">Duress</a> is a powerful addition to any control deck.  The one mana you spend on it is generally much less than you would normally have to spend to answer the threat thus gaining you tempo.  Creature destruction is another thing black offers that cannot be found in blue alone.  There are plenty of options including spot removal like <a class="mtg-card-link" rel="#mtg-card-popup" href="http://gatherer.wizards.com/Handlers/Image.ashx?size=small&type=card&name=Terror&options=" data-card="Terror">Terror</a> to mass removal like <a class="mtg-card-link" rel="#mtg-card-popup" href="http://gatherer.wizards.com/Handlers/Image.ashx?size=small&type=card&name=Infest&options=" data-card="Infest">Infest</a>.  Black also has some good card drawing effects that in some cases are as good as anything blue can muster.</p>

<p><div class="mtg-card-deck"><h3 class="mtg-card-deck-title">U/B Control</h3><div class="mtg-card-deck-content">
<div class="mtg-card-list"><h4>Lands (6)</h4><ul><li><a class="mtg-card-link" rel="#mtg-card-popup" href="http://gatherer.wizards.com/Handlers/Image.ashx?size=small&type=card&name=%3Cem%3E5%20Island&options=" data-card="&lt;em&gt;5 Island"><em>5 Island</a></li><li><a class="mtg-card-link" rel="#mtg-card-popup" href="http://gatherer.wizards.com/Handlers/Image.ashx?size=small&type=card&name=%3C/em%3E4%20Polluted%20Delta&options=" data-card="&lt;/em&gt;4 Polluted Delta"></em>4 Polluted Delta</a></li><li><a class="mtg-card-link" rel="#mtg-card-popup" href="http://gatherer.wizards.com/Handlers/Image.ashx?size=small&type=card&name=%3Cem%3E4%20Underground%20River&options=" data-card="&lt;em&gt;4 Underground River"><em>4 Underground River</a></li><li><a class="mtg-card-link" rel="#mtg-card-popup" href="http://gatherer.wizards.com/Handlers/Image.ashx?size=small&type=card&name=%3C/em%3E2%20Flooded%20Strand&options=" data-card="&lt;/em&gt;2 Flooded Strand"></em>2 Flooded Strand</a></li><li><a class="mtg-card-link" rel="#mtg-card-popup" href="http://gatherer.wizards.com/Handlers/Image.ashx?size=small&type=card&name=%3Cem%3E4%20Faerie%20Conclave&options=" data-card="&lt;em&gt;4 Faerie Conclave"><em>4 Faerie Conclave</a></li><li><a class="mtg-card-link" rel="#mtg-card-popup" href="http://gatherer.wizards.com/Handlers/Image.ashx?size=small&type=card&name=%3C/em%3E3%20Swamp&options=" data-card="&lt;/em&gt;3 Swamp"></em>3 Swamp</a></li></ul></div>
<div class="mtg-card-list"><h4>Creatures (1)</h4><ul><li><a class="mtg-card-link" rel="#mtg-card-popup" href="http://gatherer.wizards.com/Handlers/Image.ashx?size=small&type=card&name=%3Cem%3E4%20Psychatog&options=" data-card="&lt;em&gt;4 Psychatog"><em>4 Psychatog</a></li></ul></div>
<div class="mtg-card-list"><h4>Spells (9)</h4><ul><li><a class="mtg-card-link" rel="#mtg-card-popup" href="http://gatherer.wizards.com/Handlers/Image.ashx?size=small&type=card&name=%3C/em%3E4%20Counterspell&options=" data-card="&lt;/em&gt;4 Counterspell"></em>4 Counterspell</a></li><li><a class="mtg-card-link" rel="#mtg-card-popup" href="http://gatherer.wizards.com/Handlers/Image.ashx?size=small&type=card&name=%3Cem%3E4%20Mana%20Leak&options=" data-card="&lt;em&gt;4 Mana Leak"><em>4 Mana Leak</a></li><li><a class="mtg-card-link" rel="#mtg-card-popup" href="http://gatherer.wizards.com/Handlers/Image.ashx?size=small&type=card&name=%3C/em%3E4%20Undermine&options=" data-card="&lt;/em&gt;4 Undermine"></em>4 Undermine</a></li><li><a class="mtg-card-link" rel="#mtg-card-popup" href="http://gatherer.wizards.com/Handlers/Image.ashx?size=small&type=card&name=%3Cem%3E4%20Brainstorm&options=" data-card="&lt;em&gt;4 Brainstorm"><em>4 Brainstorm</a></li><li><a class="mtg-card-link" rel="#mtg-card-popup" href="http://gatherer.wizards.com/Handlers/Image.ashx?size=small&type=card&name=%3C/em%3E4%20Opt&options=" data-card="&lt;/em&gt;4 Opt"></em>4 Opt</a></li><li><a class="mtg-card-link" rel="#mtg-card-popup" href="http://gatherer.wizards.com/Handlers/Image.ashx?size=small&type=card&name=%3Cem%3E3%20Fact%20or%20Fiction&options=" data-card="&lt;em&gt;3 Fact or Fiction"><em>3 Fact or Fiction</a></li><li><a class="mtg-card-link" rel="#mtg-card-popup" href="http://gatherer.wizards.com/Handlers/Image.ashx?size=small&type=card&name=%3C/em%3E4%20Night&rsquo;s%20Whisper&options=" data-card="&lt;/em&gt;4 Night&amp;rsquo;s Whisper"></em>4 Night&rsquo;s Whisper</a></li><li><a class="mtg-card-link" rel="#mtg-card-popup" href="http://gatherer.wizards.com/Handlers/Image.ashx?size=small&type=card&name=%3Cem%3E4%20Duress&options=" data-card="&lt;em&gt;4 Duress"><em>4 Duress</a></li><li><a class="mtg-card-link" rel="#mtg-card-popup" href="http://gatherer.wizards.com/Handlers/Image.ashx?size=small&type=card&name=%3C/em%3E3%20Smother&options=" data-card="&lt;/em&gt;3 Smother"></em>3 Smother</a></li></ul></div>
</div></div></p>

<p>This deck is slightly more proactive than MUC.  This is because <a class="mtg-card-link" rel="#mtg-card-popup" href="http://gatherer.wizards.com/Handlers/Image.ashx?size=small&type=card&name=Psychatog&options=" data-card="Psychatog">Psychatog</a> is a much faster win condition than a random fatty.  It has the ability to easily do 15+ damage in a single swing generally ending the game immediately.  While 15 damage with <a class="mtg-card-link" rel="#mtg-card-popup" href="http://gatherer.wizards.com/Handlers/Image.ashx?size=small&type=card&name=Psychatog&options=" data-card="Psychatog">Psychatog</a> is easy 20 is quite difficult.  This means you&rsquo;ll need to do a bit of damage with man-lands and <a class="mtg-card-link" rel="#mtg-card-popup" href="http://gatherer.wizards.com/Handlers/Image.ashx?size=small&type=card&name=Undermine&options=" data-card="Undermine">Undermine</a> to get the opponent low enough for the Tog to be lethal.  This is actually even easier to do in a more competitive setting where 80% of the poeople are playing with painlands and fetchlands that will take a couple more life points making it that much easier for Tog to go lethal.</p>

<h3>White:</h3>

<p>The best thing white has to offer the permission deck is mass removal like <a class="mtg-card-link" rel="#mtg-card-popup" href="http://gatherer.wizards.com/Handlers/Image.ashx?size=small&type=card&name=Wrath%20of%20God&options=" data-card="Wrath of God">Wrath of God</a> this allows you to run less countermagic as you no longer have to counter creatures since you can just blow them up.  The standard U/W control deck will run something like 8+ Wrath effects.  Other helpful cards include <a class="mtg-card-link" rel="#mtg-card-popup" href="http://gatherer.wizards.com/Handlers/Image.ashx?size=small&type=card&name=Disenchant&options=" data-card="Disenchant">Disenchant</a> variants and <a class="mtg-card-link" rel="#mtg-card-popup" href="http://gatherer.wizards.com/Handlers/Image.ashx?size=small&type=card&name=Swords%20to%20Plowshares&options=" data-card="Swords to Plowshares">Swords to Plowshares</a>.</p>

<p><div class="mtg-card-deck"><h3 class="mtg-card-deck-title">U/W Control</h3><div class="mtg-card-deck-content">
<div class="mtg-card-list"><h4>Lands (5)</h4><ul><li><a class="mtg-card-link" rel="#mtg-card-popup" href="http://gatherer.wizards.com/Handlers/Image.ashx?size=small&type=card&name=%3Cem%3E6%20Island&options=" data-card="&lt;em&gt;6 Island"><em>6 Island</a></li><li><a class="mtg-card-link" rel="#mtg-card-popup" href="http://gatherer.wizards.com/Handlers/Image.ashx?size=small&type=card&name=%3C/em%3E7%20Plains&options=" data-card="&lt;/em&gt;7 Plains"></em>7 Plains</a></li><li><a class="mtg-card-link" rel="#mtg-card-popup" href="http://gatherer.wizards.com/Handlers/Image.ashx?size=small&type=card&name=%3Cem%3E4%20Flooded%20Strand&options=" data-card="&lt;em&gt;4 Flooded Strand"><em>4 Flooded Strand</a></li><li><a class="mtg-card-link" rel="#mtg-card-popup" href="http://gatherer.wizards.com/Handlers/Image.ashx?size=small&type=card&name=%3C/em%3E4%20Adarkar%20Wastes&options=" data-card="&lt;/em&gt;4 Adarkar Wastes"></em>4 Adarkar Wastes</a></li><li><a class="mtg-card-link" rel="#mtg-card-popup" href="http://gatherer.wizards.com/Handlers/Image.ashx?size=small&type=card&name=%3Cem%3E4%20Faerie%20Conclave&options=" data-card="&lt;em&gt;4 Faerie Conclave"><em>4 Faerie Conclave</a></li></ul></div>
<div class="mtg-card-list"><h4>Creatures (1)</h4><ul><li><a class="mtg-card-link" rel="#mtg-card-popup" href="http://gatherer.wizards.com/Handlers/Image.ashx?size=small&type=card&name=%3C/em%3E4%20Exalted%20Angel&options=" data-card="&lt;/em&gt;4 Exalted Angel"></em>4 Exalted Angel</a></li></ul></div>
<div class="mtg-card-list"><h4>Spells (10)</h4><ul><li><a class="mtg-card-link" rel="#mtg-card-popup" href="http://gatherer.wizards.com/Handlers/Image.ashx?size=small&type=card&name=%3Cem%3E4%20Counterspell&options=" data-card="&lt;em&gt;4 Counterspell"><em>4 Counterspell</a></li><li><a class="mtg-card-link" rel="#mtg-card-popup" href="http://gatherer.wizards.com/Handlers/Image.ashx?size=small&type=card&name=%3C/em%3E4%20Absorb&options=" data-card="&lt;/em&gt;4 Absorb"></em>4 Absorb</a></li><li><a class="mtg-card-link" rel="#mtg-card-popup" href="http://gatherer.wizards.com/Handlers/Image.ashx?size=small&type=card&name=%3Cem%3E4%20Brainstorm&options=" data-card="&lt;em&gt;4 Brainstorm"><em>4 Brainstorm</a></li><li><a class="mtg-card-link" rel="#mtg-card-popup" href="http://gatherer.wizards.com/Handlers/Image.ashx?size=small&type=card&name=%3C/em%3E4%20Accumulated%20Knowledge&options=" data-card="&lt;/em&gt;4 Accumulated Knowledge"></em>4 Accumulated Knowledge</a></li><li><a class="mtg-card-link" rel="#mtg-card-popup" href="http://gatherer.wizards.com/Handlers/Image.ashx?size=small&type=card&name=%3Cem%3E1%20Fact%20or%20Fiction&options=" data-card="&lt;em&gt;1 Fact or Fiction"><em>1 Fact or Fiction</a></li><li><a class="mtg-card-link" rel="#mtg-card-popup" href="http://gatherer.wizards.com/Handlers/Image.ashx?size=small&type=card&name=%3C/em%3E4%20Wrath%20of%20God&options=" data-card="&lt;/em&gt;4 Wrath of God"></em>4 Wrath of God</a></li><li><a class="mtg-card-link" rel="#mtg-card-popup" href="http://gatherer.wizards.com/Handlers/Image.ashx?size=small&type=card&name=%3Cem%3E4%20Akroma&rsquo;s%20Vengeance&options=" data-card="&lt;em&gt;4 Akroma&amp;rsquo;s Vengeance"><em>4 Akroma&rsquo;s Vengeance</a></li><li><a class="mtg-card-link" rel="#mtg-card-popup" href="http://gatherer.wizards.com/Handlers/Image.ashx?size=small&type=card&name=%3C/em%3E4%20Swords%20to%20Plowshares&options=" data-card="&lt;/em&gt;4 Swords to Plowshares"></em>4 Swords to Plowshares</a></li><li><span class="mtg-card-list-quantity">2</span> <a class="mtg-card-link" rel="#mtg-card-popup" href="http://gatherer.wizards.com/Handlers/Image.ashx?size=small&type=card&name=Dismantling%20Blow&options=" data-card="Dismantling Blow">Dismantling Blow</a></li></ul></div>
</div></div></p>

<p>Try to save your Wrath effects for when you can kill more than one creature.  Unlike MUC you can drop your win condition a bit earlier with this deck as the lifegain on the Angel will let you race much better.</p>

<h3>Green:</h3>

<p>Green provides the best mana acceleration in the game.  Since control decks are very mana hungry this is a good thing.  It also provides the ability to reuse cards via cards like <a class="mtg-card-link" rel="#mtg-card-popup" href="http://gatherer.wizards.com/Handlers/Image.ashx?size=small&type=card&name=Regrowth&options=" data-card="Regrowth">Regrowth</a>, <a class="mtg-card-link" rel="#mtg-card-popup" href="http://gatherer.wizards.com/Handlers/Image.ashx?size=small&type=card&name=Eternal%20Witness&options=" data-card="Eternal Witness">Eternal Witness</a>, and <a class="mtg-card-link" rel="#mtg-card-popup" href="http://gatherer.wizards.com/Handlers/Image.ashx?size=small&type=card&name=Gaea&rsquo;s%20Blessing&options=" data-card="Gaea&amp;rsquo;s Blessing">Gaea&rsquo;s Blessing</a>.  Beyond that it really just offers <a class="mtg-card-link" rel="#mtg-card-popup" href="http://gatherer.wizards.com/Handlers/Image.ashx?size=small&type=card&name=Naturalize&options=" data-card="Naturalize">Naturalize</a> and a few random cards like <a class="mtg-card-link" rel="#mtg-card-popup" href="http://gatherer.wizards.com/Handlers/Image.ashx?size=small&type=card&name=Plow%20Under&options=" data-card="Plow Under">Plow Under</a>.  Even if it looks like green offers less than other colors what it does offer can be quite powerful.</p>

<p><div class="mtg-card-deck"><h3 class="mtg-card-deck-title">U/G Control</h3><div class="mtg-card-deck-content">
<div class="mtg-card-list"><h4>Lands (5)</h4><ul><li><a class="mtg-card-link" rel="#mtg-card-popup" href="http://gatherer.wizards.com/Handlers/Image.ashx?size=small&type=card&name=%3Cem%3E6%20Island&options=" data-card="&lt;em&gt;6 Island"><em>6 Island</a></li><li><a class="mtg-card-link" rel="#mtg-card-popup" href="http://gatherer.wizards.com/Handlers/Image.ashx?size=small&type=card&name=%3C/em%3E6%20Forest&options=" data-card="&lt;/em&gt;6 Forest"></em>6 Forest</a></li><li><a class="mtg-card-link" rel="#mtg-card-popup" href="http://gatherer.wizards.com/Handlers/Image.ashx?size=small&type=card&name=%3Cem%3E4%20Yavimaya%20Coast&options=" data-card="&lt;em&gt;4 Yavimaya Coast"><em>4 Yavimaya Coast</a></li><li><a class="mtg-card-link" rel="#mtg-card-popup" href="http://gatherer.wizards.com/Handlers/Image.ashx?size=small&type=card&name=%3C/em%3E4%20Treetop%20Village&options=" data-card="&lt;/em&gt;4 Treetop Village"></em>4 Treetop Village</a></li><li><a class="mtg-card-link" rel="#mtg-card-popup" href="http://gatherer.wizards.com/Handlers/Image.ashx?size=small&type=card&name=%3Cem%3E4%20Faerie%20Conclave&options=" data-card="&lt;em&gt;4 Faerie Conclave"><em>4 Faerie Conclave</a></li></ul></div>
<div class="mtg-card-list"><h4>Creatures (4)</h4><ul><li><a class="mtg-card-link" rel="#mtg-card-popup" href="http://gatherer.wizards.com/Handlers/Image.ashx?size=small&type=card&name=%3C/em%3E4%20Mystic%20Snake&options=" data-card="&lt;/em&gt;4 Mystic Snake"></em>4 Mystic Snake</a></li><li><a class="mtg-card-link" rel="#mtg-card-popup" href="http://gatherer.wizards.com/Handlers/Image.ashx?size=small&type=card&name=%3Cem%3E4%20Eternal%20Witness&options=" data-card="&lt;em&gt;4 Eternal Witness"><em>4 Eternal Witness</a></li><li><a class="mtg-card-link" rel="#mtg-card-popup" href="http://gatherer.wizards.com/Handlers/Image.ashx?size=small&type=card&name=%3C/em%3E2%20Meloku%20the%20Clouded%20Mirror&options=" data-card="&lt;/em&gt;2 Meloku the Clouded Mirror"></em>2 Meloku the Clouded Mirror</a></li><li><a class="mtg-card-link" rel="#mtg-card-popup" href="http://gatherer.wizards.com/Handlers/Image.ashx?size=small&type=card&name=%3Cem%3E4%20Sakura-Tribe%20Elder&options=" data-card="&lt;em&gt;4 Sakura-Tribe Elder"><em>4 Sakura-Tribe Elder</a></li></ul></div>
<div class="mtg-card-list"><h4>Spells (7)</h4><ul><li><a class="mtg-card-link" rel="#mtg-card-popup" href="http://gatherer.wizards.com/Handlers/Image.ashx?size=small&type=card&name=%3C/em%3E4%20Counterspell&options=" data-card="&lt;/em&gt;4 Counterspell"></em>4 Counterspell</a></li><li><a class="mtg-card-link" rel="#mtg-card-popup" href="http://gatherer.wizards.com/Handlers/Image.ashx?size=small&type=card&name=%3Cem%3E4%20Mana%20Leak&options=" data-card="&lt;em&gt;4 Mana Leak"><em>4 Mana Leak</a></li><li><a class="mtg-card-link" rel="#mtg-card-popup" href="http://gatherer.wizards.com/Handlers/Image.ashx?size=small&type=card&name=%3C/em%3E4%20Standstill&options=" data-card="&lt;/em&gt;4 Standstill"></em>4 Standstill</a></li><li><a class="mtg-card-link" rel="#mtg-card-popup" href="http://gatherer.wizards.com/Handlers/Image.ashx?size=small&type=card&name=%3Cem%3E1%20Rude%20Awakening&options=" data-card="&lt;em&gt;1 Rude Awakening"><em>1 Rude Awakening</a></li><li><a class="mtg-card-link" rel="#mtg-card-popup" href="http://gatherer.wizards.com/Handlers/Image.ashx?size=small&type=card&name=%3C/em%3E3%20Kodama&rsquo;s%20Reach&options=" data-card="&lt;/em&gt;3 Kodama&amp;rsquo;s Reach"></em>3 Kodama&rsquo;s Reach</a></li><li><a class="mtg-card-link" rel="#mtg-card-popup" href="http://gatherer.wizards.com/Handlers/Image.ashx?size=small&type=card&name=%3Cem%3E4%20Nevinyrral&rsquo;s%20Disk&options=" data-card="&lt;em&gt;4 Nevinyrral&amp;rsquo;s Disk"><em>4 Nevinyrral&rsquo;s Disk</a></li><li><a class="mtg-card-link" rel="#mtg-card-popup" href="http://gatherer.wizards.com/Handlers/Image.ashx?size=small&type=card&name=%3C/em%3E2%20Naturalize&options=" data-card="&lt;/em&gt;2 Naturalize"></em>2 Naturalize</a></li></ul></div>
</div></div></p>

<p>You can sort of treat this as a landstill deck.  Try to drop a <a class="mtg-card-link" rel="#mtg-card-popup" href="http://gatherer.wizards.com/Handlers/Image.ashx?size=small&type=card&name=Standstill&options=" data-card="Standstill">Standstill</a> when you have the only threat on the board.  Remember that lands don&rsquo;t count as spells and many of yours can attack so use that to your advantage.</p>

<h3>Red:</h3>

<p>Red provides burn, burn, and more burn.  This can either be used as removal or go to the dome.  While using burn as removal can certainly be effective it isn&rsquo;t all that different than running black or white for the same thing.  The real strength of burn is its flexibility in that it can be both removal and a win condition.  Counter burn decks are nothing new to magic and can be both effective and fun to play.</p>

<p><div class="mtg-card-deck"><h3 class="mtg-card-deck-title">U/R Control</h3><div class="mtg-card-deck-content">
<div class="mtg-card-list"><h4>Lands (4)</h4><ul><li><a class="mtg-card-link" rel="#mtg-card-popup" href="http://gatherer.wizards.com/Handlers/Image.ashx?size=small&type=card&name=%3Cem%3E7%20Island&options=" data-card="&lt;em&gt;7 Island"><em>7 Island</a></li><li><a class="mtg-card-link" rel="#mtg-card-popup" href="http://gatherer.wizards.com/Handlers/Image.ashx?size=small&type=card&name=%3C/em%3E4%20Shivan%20Reef&options=" data-card="&lt;/em&gt;4 Shivan Reef"></em>4 Shivan Reef</a></li><li><a class="mtg-card-link" rel="#mtg-card-popup" href="http://gatherer.wizards.com/Handlers/Image.ashx?size=small&type=card&name=%3Cem%3E7%20Mountain&options=" data-card="&lt;em&gt;7 Mountain"><em>7 Mountain</a></li><li><a class="mtg-card-link" rel="#mtg-card-popup" href="http://gatherer.wizards.com/Handlers/Image.ashx?size=small&type=card&name=%3C/em%3E4%20Faerie%20Conclave&options=" data-card="&lt;/em&gt;4 Faerie Conclave"></em>4 Faerie Conclave</a></li></ul></div>
<div class="mtg-card-list"><h4>Creatures (1)</h4><ul><li><a class="mtg-card-link" rel="#mtg-card-popup" href="http://gatherer.wizards.com/Handlers/Image.ashx?size=small&type=card&name=%3Cem%3E4%20Frenetic%20Efreet&options=" data-card="&lt;em&gt;4 Frenetic Efreet"><em>4 Frenetic Efreet</a></li></ul></div>
<div class="mtg-card-list"><h4>Spells (11)</h4><ul><li><a class="mtg-card-link" rel="#mtg-card-popup" href="http://gatherer.wizards.com/Handlers/Image.ashx?size=small&type=card&name=%3C/em%3E4%20Counterspell&options=" data-card="&lt;/em&gt;4 Counterspell"></em>4 Counterspell</a></li><li><a class="mtg-card-link" rel="#mtg-card-popup" href="http://gatherer.wizards.com/Handlers/Image.ashx?size=small&type=card&name=%3Cem%3E4%20Mana%20Leak&options=" data-card="&lt;em&gt;4 Mana Leak"><em>4 Mana Leak</a></li><li><a class="mtg-card-link" rel="#mtg-card-popup" href="http://gatherer.wizards.com/Handlers/Image.ashx?size=small&type=card&name=%3C/em%3E2%20Suffocating%20Blast&options=" data-card="&lt;/em&gt;2 Suffocating Blast"></em>2 Suffocating Blast</a></li><li><a class="mtg-card-link" rel="#mtg-card-popup" href="http://gatherer.wizards.com/Handlers/Image.ashx?size=small&type=card&name=%3Cem%3E2%20Dissipate&options=" data-card="&lt;em&gt;2 Dissipate"><em>2 Dissipate</a></li><li><a class="mtg-card-link" rel="#mtg-card-popup" href="http://gatherer.wizards.com/Handlers/Image.ashx?size=small&type=card&name=%3C/em%3E4%20Accumulated%20Knowledge&options=" data-card="&lt;/em&gt;4 Accumulated Knowledge"></em>4 Accumulated Knowledge</a></li><li><a class="mtg-card-link" rel="#mtg-card-popup" href="http://gatherer.wizards.com/Handlers/Image.ashx?size=small&type=card&name=%3Cem%3E4%20Whispers%20of%20the%20Muse&options=" data-card="&lt;em&gt;4 Whispers of the Muse"><em>4 Whispers of the Muse</a></li><li><a class="mtg-card-link" rel="#mtg-card-popup" href="http://gatherer.wizards.com/Handlers/Image.ashx?size=small&type=card&name=%3C/em%3E4%20Lightning%20Bolt&options=" data-card="&lt;/em&gt;4 Lightning Bolt"></em>4 Lightning Bolt</a></li><li><a class="mtg-card-link" rel="#mtg-card-popup" href="http://gatherer.wizards.com/Handlers/Image.ashx?size=small&type=card&name=%3Cem%3E4%20Incinerate&options=" data-card="&lt;em&gt;4 Incinerate"><em>4 Incinerate</a></li><li><a class="mtg-card-link" rel="#mtg-card-popup" href="http://gatherer.wizards.com/Handlers/Image.ashx?size=small&type=card&name=%3C/em%3E4%20Fire%20//%20Ice&options=" data-card="&lt;/em&gt;4 Fire // Ice"></em>4 Fire // Ice</a></li><li><span class="mtg-card-list-quantity">2</span> <a class="mtg-card-link" rel="#mtg-card-popup" href="http://gatherer.wizards.com/Handlers/Image.ashx?size=small&type=card&name=Starstorm&options=" data-card="Starstorm">Starstorm</a></li></ul></div>
</div></div></p>

<p>Spend the early turns playing land.  Once you have the mana to counter spells and use your burn go for it making sure you only use it at the end of your opponent&rsquo;s turn.  All the spells here are instants so you will rarely do much beyond playing a land during your own turn.</p>

<h2>Playing Against the Deck:</h2>

<p>If you understand how to play with a control deck you can understand how to beat one.</p>

<p><strong>Rule #1:</strong> You are the beatdown.</p>

<p>Don&rsquo;t try to be reactive.  You will never out control the most controlling deck type.  Your job is to provide the threats and make them find the answers.  As Dan Paskins has been quoted many times for saying There are no wrong threats, only wrong answers.</p>

<p><strong>Rule #2:</strong> Don&rsquo;t be afraid of counters.</p>

<p>Your opponent wants you to hold back.  This will give him time to draw into more counters and control cards.  The more time the control deck has the more likely it is going to win.  They want you to believe they always have counters don&rsquo;t buy into that.</p>

<p><strong>Rule #3:</strong> Use less important spells to draw out countermagic first.</p>

<p>You want your opponent to use as much countermagic as possible.  This maximizes the chance that they are going to run out.  Keep in mind that the average MUC deck has about 12-14 counters max.  The average aggro deck has something like 20-25+ threats.  If you draw enough they will run out before you.  Make sure to make this happen as quickly as possible then capitalize on it before they draw more.  They likely are drawing more cards than you so time is very important.</p>

<p><strong>Rule #4:</strong> Be confident.</p>

<p>It may be annoying to have all of your spells countered and it may seem like they have an endless supply of answers and act like they know it.  Don&rsquo;t believe them.  Playing the control deck can be a terrifying thing.  It is often a desperate act of digging for your next answer and hoping your opponent never learns you aren&rsquo;t as invulnerable as you seem.  You probably just burned their last counter on your mid-sized creature and have nothing left for the other one you are holding and are counting on that top decked <a class="mtg-card-link" rel="#mtg-card-popup" href="http://gatherer.wizards.com/Handlers/Image.ashx?size=small&type=card&name=Fact%20or%20Fiction&options=" data-card="Fact or Fiction">Fact or Fiction</a> to get another one.  This is not always true but there is almost always at least one point in a game where the control deck can do nothing but pray.  It is your job to find this point and exploit it.</p>

<p><strong>Rule #5:</strong> Counterspell costs 2 mana.</p>

<p>Unless they have <a class="mtg-card-link" rel="#mtg-card-popup" href="http://gatherer.wizards.com/Handlers/Image.ashx?size=small&type=card&name=Force%20of%20Will&options=" data-card="Force of Will">Force of Will</a> or <a class="mtg-card-link" rel="#mtg-card-popup" href="http://gatherer.wizards.com/Handlers/Image.ashx?size=small&type=card&name=Force%20Spike&options=" data-card="Force Spike">Force Spike</a> or something similar you are likely free to do anything on turn 1.  An aggressive 1-drop can take out quite a bit of life before the control deck can neutralize it.  Something like <a class="mtg-card-link" rel="#mtg-card-popup" href="http://gatherer.wizards.com/Handlers/Image.ashx?size=small&type=card&name=Jackal%20Pup&options=" data-card="Jackal Pup">Jackal Pup</a>, <a class="mtg-card-link" rel="#mtg-card-popup" href="http://gatherer.wizards.com/Handlers/Image.ashx?size=small&type=card&name=Carnophage&options=" data-card="Carnophage">Carnophage</a>, or <a class="mtg-card-link" rel="#mtg-card-popup" href="http://gatherer.wizards.com/Handlers/Image.ashx?size=small&type=card&name=Savannah%20Lions&options=" data-card="Savannah Lions">Savannah Lions</a> can deal much more damage than the control deck would like before being neutralized.</p>

<p><strong>Rule #6:</strong> Discard is great.</p>

<p>Cheap discard is quite possibly the most powerful weapon against a control deck.  Take for example <a class="mtg-card-link" rel="#mtg-card-popup" href="http://gatherer.wizards.com/Handlers/Image.ashx?size=small&type=card&name=Duress&options=" data-card="Duress">Duress</a>.  You are likely going to use it to take a counter from your opponent.  What is your opponent going to do about that?  Counter it?  That will just tap mana to accomplish exactly what you want them to do.  Cheap discard spells that cost no more mana than the counterspells are probably the best weapon to use against countermagic period.</p>

<p><strong>Rule #7:</strong> Not everything can be countered.</p>

<p>There are plenty of spells that you just plain can&rsquo;t counter.  Something like <a class="mtg-card-link" rel="#mtg-card-popup" href="http://gatherer.wizards.com/Handlers/Image.ashx?size=small&type=card&name=Mishra&rsquo;s%20Factory&options=" data-card="Mishra&amp;rsquo;s Factory">Mishra&rsquo;s Factory</a>, <a class="mtg-card-link" rel="#mtg-card-popup" href="http://gatherer.wizards.com/Handlers/Image.ashx?size=small&type=card&name=Blurred%20Mongoose&options=" data-card="Blurred Mongoose">Blurred Mongoose</a>, or <a class="mtg-card-link" rel="#mtg-card-popup" href="http://gatherer.wizards.com/Handlers/Image.ashx?size=small&type=card&name=Scragnoth&options=" data-card="Scragnoth">Scragnoth</a> will provide a threat that many times is just impossible to deal with.  The cycling triggers from Onslaught block are also uncounterable outside of cards like <a class="mtg-card-link" rel="#mtg-card-popup" href="http://gatherer.wizards.com/Handlers/Image.ashx?size=small&type=card&name=Stifle&options=" data-card="Stifle">Stifle</a>.</p>

<p><strong>Rule #8:</strong> Recursion is awesome.</p>

<p>Anything that lets you cast the same threat multiple times can cause problems for the control deck.  Creatures like <a class="mtg-card-link" rel="#mtg-card-popup" href="http://gatherer.wizards.com/Handlers/Image.ashx?size=small&type=card&name=Gigapede&options=" data-card="Gigapede">Gigapede</a>, <a class="mtg-card-link" rel="#mtg-card-popup" href="http://gatherer.wizards.com/Handlers/Image.ashx?size=small&type=card&name=Coffin%20Puppets&options=" data-card="Coffin Puppets">Coffin Puppets</a>, and <a class="mtg-card-link" rel="#mtg-card-popup" href="http://gatherer.wizards.com/Handlers/Image.ashx?size=small&type=card&name=Nether%20Spirit&options=" data-card="Nether Spirit">Nether Spirit</a> can often win the game as countering it just buys a bit of time.  They will run out of countermagic eventually and this is when you get to have fun.  This also applies to engines such as <a class="mtg-card-link" rel="#mtg-card-popup" href="http://gatherer.wizards.com/Handlers/Image.ashx?size=small&type=card&name=Genesis&options=" data-card="Genesis">Genesis</a>, <a class="mtg-card-link" rel="#mtg-card-popup" href="http://gatherer.wizards.com/Handlers/Image.ashx?size=small&type=card&name=Oath%20of%20Ghouls&options=" data-card="Oath of Ghouls">Oath of Ghouls</a>, <a class="mtg-card-link" rel="#mtg-card-popup" href="http://gatherer.wizards.com/Handlers/Image.ashx?size=small&type=card&name=Oversold%20Cemetery&options=" data-card="Oversold Cemetery">Oversold Cemetery</a>.</p>

<p><strong>Rule #9:</strong> Control decks are mana intensive.</p>

<p>Likely they need more mana than you.  This means anything that can deny them that is excellent.  Traditional land destruction isn&rsquo;t always that good since those decks are threat light but cards like <a class="mtg-card-link" rel="#mtg-card-popup" href="http://gatherer.wizards.com/Handlers/Image.ashx?size=small&type=card&name=Strip%20Mine&options=" data-card="Strip Mine">Strip Mine</a>, <a class="mtg-card-link" rel="#mtg-card-popup" href="http://gatherer.wizards.com/Handlers/Image.ashx?size=small&type=card&name=Wasteland&options=" data-card="Wasteland">Wasteland</a>, <a class="mtg-card-link" rel="#mtg-card-popup" href="http://gatherer.wizards.com/Handlers/Image.ashx?size=small&type=card&name=Armageddon&options=" data-card="Armageddon">Armageddon</a>, <a class="mtg-card-link" rel="#mtg-card-popup" href="http://gatherer.wizards.com/Handlers/Image.ashx?size=small&type=card&name=Winter%20Orb&options=" data-card="Winter Orb">Winter Orb</a>, and <a class="mtg-card-link" rel="#mtg-card-popup" href="http://gatherer.wizards.com/Handlers/Image.ashx?size=small&type=card&name=Static%20Orb&options=" data-card="Static Orb">Static Orb</a> give control players many problems.  A control player never wants to play against a deck with <a class="mtg-card-link" rel="#mtg-card-popup" href="http://gatherer.wizards.com/Handlers/Image.ashx?size=small&type=card&name=Obliterate&options=" data-card="Obliterate">Obliterate</a> as the only out is <a class="mtg-card-link" rel="#mtg-card-popup" href="http://gatherer.wizards.com/Handlers/Image.ashx?size=small&type=card&name=Time%20Stop&options=" data-card="Time Stop">Time Stop</a>.</p>

<h2>Conclusion:</h2>

<p>I hope this gives you more of an understanding on how to build, play with, and play against a counter heavy control deck.  Control would not be as big a problem as it is in our group if there were more anti-control threats out there.  Beating control isn&rsquo;t as hard as you would think.</p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
</feed>
